<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ready path to the pleasant pasture of delitesome and eternall paradyse so called, bicause herein is declared how, and by what meanes, we shall easily obtayne the surprising pleasures of heauenly felicitie.</title>
            <author>I. T. fl. 1570.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23621.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2915</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29457562</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29457562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13312)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 582:10 or 1859:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ready path to the pleasant pasture of delitesome and eternall paradyse so called, bicause herein is declared how, and by what meanes, we shall easily obtayne the surprising pleasures of heauenly felicitie.</title>
                  <author>I. T. fl. 1570.</author>
                  <author>J. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted at London by Henry Denham for Iohn Hudson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1570?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed I.T. [i.e. J.T.?]</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴-O⁴, P³; A repeated, B not present.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: at reel 1859:10, pages torn, tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of text; at 582:10 part of preliminaries lacking.</note>
                  <note>"Seene and allowed according to the order appointed."</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 23622 at reel 582:10.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Harvard University Library (reel 1859) and Folger Shakespeare Library (reel 582).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27972:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27972:1"/>
            <p>The ready Path to the pleaſant Pasture of deliteſome, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Paradyſe, ſo called, bicauſe herein is declared how, and by what meanes, we ſhall eaſily obtayne the ſurpaſsing pleaſures of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</p>
            <p>Scene and allowed according to the order appointed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ioel. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Omnis qui inuocauerit nomen Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, ſaluus erit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euery one that ſhall call vppon the name of the Lorde, ſhall be ſafe.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London by <hi>Henry Denham, for</hi> Iohn Iudſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:27972:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27972:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT THE WHOLE worlde be miſerably plunged, and daungerouſly drowned in the terrible ſeas of Gods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie wrath, and ſore diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet (moſt deare chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) ſuch are the vnſpeakeable riches, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable treaſures of his heauenly mercy, that be wyll not diſdaine to relieue vs, to ſaue vs, to helpe vs, to holde vs, to heale vs, and to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vs, in the moſt pleaſaunt, and comfortable reſt of his most gracious, and eternall fauour, if with humble mindes, with ſorowfull, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunt heartes, wyth a conſtaunt, and liuely fayth, we will proſtrate our ſelues before the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting throne of his immortall Maiestie, hoping to be mercyfullye, paciently, and graciouſlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, onely for the merites of Chriſt Ieſus, our onely triumphant, and mightie Sauiour. But bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men nowe in theſe our dayes are in hart hardened, in lyfe lycentious, in loue laſciuious, in maners miſerable, in wordes wylfull, in ſenſe vnſauerie, in doings diſordered, in talke vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, in wyt wylde, in reaſon retchleſſe, in rage vnreaſonable, in foly forwarde, in fanſie fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:3"/>
in vice venimous, in vylanie vaunting, in ſoule ſinfull, in charitie colde, in furie fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, in faith fruitleſſe, and to conclude, in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning themſelues graceleſſe, and godleſſe: it is neceſſarie before they can haue acceſſe to God in mercie through Chriſt Ieſus, before they can paſſe to the moſt pleaſaunt habitation of Gods euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and immortall kingdome, before they can be enfraunchiſed CytiZens in heauenly Ieruſalem, that they expell pride, baniſhe arrogancie, expell hypocriſie, deteſt all impietie, clenſe awaye the dregges of ſtinking Poperie, waſhe out the ſpottes of diſobedient adulterie, and wype out the blemiſh of all blaſphemous ydolatrie, which by none other meanes can more conueniently bee brought to paſſe, then by conſideration of the terrible threates of God againſt obſtinate, harde hearted, and rebellious aduerſaries, againſt ſtifnecked, vngra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and diſobedient ſeruaunts, againſt vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, vnthankefull, and graceleſſe children, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, which contemptuouſlye diſpiſe his commaundements, which ſpitefully neglect his fatherly counſell, which wylfully tranſgreſſe his holye lawes, which diſobediently refuſe to giue eare to his aduiſe and cenſure, which voluntarily caſt themſelues headlong, into the perillous pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:3"/>
and gaping goulfe of all abhominable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſſe, vnlawfull wickedneſſe, and extreme miſerie. I haue therefore (deare christian) in this my ſhort treatiſe, wherein my principall, and eſpeciall purpoſe is to bring men to the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, profitable, and holeſome exerciſe of godly prayer, firſt declared the horrible eſtate, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death of ſuch, who doe not, and will not prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe earneſt, and hartie prayer, nowe whileſt God doth lende them leaſure, and giue them oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, to reforme their looſeneſſe of lyfe, to returne vnto him with hope of mercie, to eſcape the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce ready to be poured out vpon ſtifneckned ſinners. I haue (I ſay) firſt declared, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly proued, that ſuch, vnleſſe they repent, ſhall haue none other ende, but eternall condemnation in the bottomleſſe pit of hell fire in moſt bitter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nguiſh &amp; immortal miſerie. Secondarily I haue plainely ſet foorth with certaine proofe, the moſt happie ende, the bliſfull eſtate, the good condition of thoſe, who with hartie minde, and earneſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and pure Zeale imbrace the godlye prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of perfite prayer. By the firſt part, the terror of Gods intollerable vengeaunce maye batter downe the ſtrong walles of prowde, and vnbroken hartes, by the ſeconde, the bruſed conſciences of
<pb facs="tcp:27972:4"/>
the ſorowfull christians, may be happily repaired, and raiſed vp againe. By the firſt, ſleepy ſecurity may holeſomely be baniſhed, by the ſecond, godly certainetie of ſaluation maye eaſily be procured, through the firſt, mans hart maye be wounded, through the ſecond, it may be ſalued, by the firſt mans mind is, as it were, launched, by the ſecond, healed, by the firſt, roughly ſcoured, by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond freſhely bewtified, by the firſt, opened, by the ſecond clenſed, by the firſt, cut out, and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, by the ſecond, poliſhed, by the firſt, halfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the bondes of cruell Sathan, by the ſecond, ſafely brought into the gracious fauour of our immortall Sauiour. Thirdly, leaſt ſomething ſhould ſeeme to bee wanting, for the better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the ſimple Christians, I haue brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye giuen certaine rules, and precepts, wherewith if alwayes our prayers be well ordered, we ſhall vndoubtedly obtaine our good requeſtes at the handes of God, which thing aſſuredly as it is profitable at all times, ſo in theſe our moſt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and wofull dayes, it is moſt neceſſarie. For when our enimies doe inuade vs, it is then tyme to prepare to battaile. When vice raigneth, then it is neceſſarie to ſee, that vertue be ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. When Sathan triumpheth, then it is highe
<pb facs="tcp:27972:4"/>
time to pray, that he may be diſplaced. When true humilitie once is defaced, then it is time for hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryſie to be ſuppreſſed, and nowe when rebels rage, ſometime in inward cogitations, ſometimes in outward irruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, it is neceſſary for the helth, and ſafegarde of good christians with earneſt and hartie mindes, to deſire God, that all their enimious wicked enterpriſes maye bee confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, their endeuours ouerturned, their deuilliſh purpoſes altogither diſappointed, and that the princely eſtate of our moſt gracious, and godly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lady, Queene EliZabeth, may for euer bee mightily preſerued, worthily maintained, and moſt proſperouſly confirmed, which I beſeech God in the bowels of Chriſt Ieſus mercyfullye to graunt. For prayer in what eſtate ſoeuer we be, is eyther our onely ſtay, comfort, refuge, and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or elſe our principall defence, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde. There withall the ſubtile aſſaultes of craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Sathan are eaſily eſcaped, his ſleightes auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, his rage refrayned, his furie brideled, and all his endeuours vtterly disturbed. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, by prayer eſpecially the mercies of God are liberally graunted, his grace obtayned, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour founde, his loue allured, and his gracious goodneſſe bountyfully beſtowed. Wherefore let vs
<pb facs="tcp:27972:5"/>
imbrace the godly practiſe of hartie prayer, as the ſure ſeale of our eternall ſaluation, as the pledge of our redemption, as the certaine token of our bleſſed election, and ſo vndoubtedly wee ſhall at the last raigne for euer, and euer with Chriſt in all felicitie in his glorious, and immortall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which he graunt for the merites of his moſt precious paſsion, to whome with the father, and the holy ghoſt, be all honor, praiſe, and glory, world without ende. Amen.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue our Noble Queene ElyZabeth, and ſende continuall peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt hir louing ſubiectes.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27972:5"/>
            <head>¶ The readie path to the <hi>pleaſaunt pasture of</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteſome, and eternall <hi>Paradiſe. &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>How gracious, fauourable, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God is to his creature man, and of his firſt fall, and the decay of his ſucceſſors or poſteritie. <hi>The first Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the grieuous ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination of our poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſpitefull heartes, the moſt execrable endes of our malicious, and deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe endeuours, the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous villanies of our diſdainefull, deadly, and deſperate impietie, doe deſerue moſt terrible tormentes, moſt heauie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, moſt bitter, and eternall anguiſhe, in the bottomleſſe pit of perdition, without redemption: yet the mercifull goodneſſe, and vnſpeakeable kindneſſe of God, our tender father, our carefull kéeper, our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:27972:6"/>
ſauiour, doth not onelye caſt vs head-long (which we deſerue) into that daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous darkeneſſe, and gaping goulfe, which burneth with fire and brimſtone, where is continuall wéeping and gnaſhing of téeth: but alſo moſt gently calleth vs againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that we may taſte of his mercies, moſt pitifully bewayleth our wickedneſſe, moſt heartilye forgetteth our iniquities, moſt carefully cutteth off our corruption, moſt readily repayreth our empaired and depraued nature, moſt willingly wincketh at our detected enormities, moſt graciouſly couereth our ſhamefull nakedneſſe, moſt mightily maintayneth our cauſe agaynſt our open aduerſarie the Deuill, moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſireth our health and ſaluation, moſt attentiuely wayteth for our godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, moſt largely promiſeth vs a glorious crowne and eternall kingdome, with frée deliueraunce, and preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, if with pure heart and true zeale wée ſhall cal vpon his holy name, and ſéeke ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour in Ieſus Chriſt, of his immortal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. For when he of his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and excéeding mercy, did firſt frame
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27972:6"/>
and forme our father Adam, and rayſed him vppe oute of the ſlimie bowels of the fruitfull earth, when he had breathed into him the ſpirite of life, when he had endued his reaſonable ſoule with the bright bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of moſt perfite knowledge, and had beſtowed vpon him the blaſing lightes of moſt excellent &amp; approued vertues, when he had giuen him the ſoueraigne ſcience both of celeſtial, earthly, heauenly, mortal, and immortall things, when he had giuen him power ouer all the creatures, which were vnder the cope of heauen, and had for this onely cauſe builded the wyde worlde, that man his moſte noble and ſurpaſſing creature, might with all maner of delite, enioy the commodities of the ſame, and at the laſt, when he had placed him in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, being a place of pleaſure, a paſture of delites, a moſt ſwéete, pleaſaunt, and fruitfull garden, and licenced him to taſte of all the fruits and pleaſures of the ſame, wherein he might for euer haue led a moſt happie life, and neuer haue felt the bitter pangues of extreeme dolor, wherwith now he is compaſſed and beſet of euery ſide (on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:27972:7"/>
charging him to abſtaine from the trée of knowledge of good and euill, enioyning therevnto a ſeuere puniſhment the more to reſtraine him: than this wilfull, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne, and vnthankefull man, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with this heauenly ſtate, but aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the iuſt and expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of his louing father, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall creator to ſuche daungerous and deuiliſh knowledge, wherby was wrought his vtter deſtruction and miſerable confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; gaue eare to the contagious councell and peſtilent perſwaſion of enchaunted and bewitched Eua, who by the ſugred tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the curſed Sathan, receyued the impoyſoned bayt which was couered with falſe, faire, and fayned promiſes, whereby they were both ſo fowlye ſpotted, and ſo miſerablye deformed, that where before they had the ſimilitude of God engraffed in their heartes, nowe they were plaine patternes and expreſſe images of the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſerpent: where before they were ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtarres illuminate with the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome light of the heauenly ſpirit, now they were darke and miſtie clowdes, deſtitute
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27972:7"/>
of all clereneſſe, and clad with moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble impietie: where before they were dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and adorned with ſingular integritie, iuſtice, and puritie, nowe they were beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blemiſhed with the filthie ſpots of wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched villanie, pride, and impuritie: where before they were chiefe inhabitaunts, and principall poſſeſſors of pereleſſe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt Paradiſe, nowe they were become exiled ſtraungers, expelled vagaboundes, and beggars baniſhed from all felicitie: where before they were obedient ſeruants nowe they were rebellious enimies: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore friendes of God, nowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endes of hell: before in bleſſefull eſtate, nowe in damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and extréeme miſerie: before almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with Aungels, now worſe than De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils: before better than all earthly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, now more abhominable than brute beaſtes: before the louing ſonnes of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der father, now the open aduerſaries of a ſeuere Iudge: before cheriſhed and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued children, now falſe and forſworne fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons: before bleſſed and immortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, now curſed and mortall myſers: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without trouble and anguiſhe, nowe
<pb facs="tcp:27972:8"/>
oppreſſed with calamitie, griefe, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: before without contagion, now ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſickneſſe: before euer ioyfull, nowe for euer ſorrowfull: before neuer comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, nowe alwayes in themſelues hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and helpeleſſe: before puyſſant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nowe pelting peaſants: before polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; precious paragons of vertue, nowe péeuiſh and polluted Pagans: before par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of eternall happineſſe, nowe méete firebrandes of terrible tormentes: before ſacred Temples of the holy ghoſt, now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed and ſtinking chanels of all ſinfull vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie, retchleſſe, crooked, crabbed, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous impietie. And, alas, into this ſo pitious a plight, ſo miſerable a caſe, ſo gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous a daunger, and ſo preſent perdition, we poore wretches, which be their vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſonnes, their damned ofſpring, their wicked progenie, are by their heynous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and our owne corruption fallen and entrapped, from the which we through our owne ſelues, or our owne ſtrength, can neuer be deliuered, but do dayly more and more by vaine cogitations, by diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dealings, by curſed hypocriſie, by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27972:8"/>
obſtinacie, by ſwelling pride, by lothſome hate, by cankerd contempt, by deuiliſhe enuie, by ſléepie ſecuritie, by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in prayer, by diligence in euill doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by outragious oppreſſion of the poore, by defrauding of the ſimple, by ſpoyling widowes, by deceyuing orphanes, by tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly neglecting and nothing regarding our bounden duties, doe prouoke to wrath the almighty God, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell him to poure downe his heauie plagues and grieuous indignation vpon vs, to our vtter ruine and confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The promiſe of Chriſt the Redemer of man, and his conqueſt to deliuer him out of thraldome, and our dutie contrary. <hi>The ſecond Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt in this our damnable eſtate and condition, when we could ſée nothing but deadlye deſperation, and the monſtruous mouth of the burning pitte of hell readie to receyue vs, then oure excéeding good, gracious, and
<pb facs="tcp:27972:9"/>
gentle God, whome before we had ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefully forſaken, ſo daungerouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed, ſo villainouſly contemned, ſo lewdly diſpleaſed, ſo maliciouſly prouoked, ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully caſt off and reiected, that we had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to follow the ſong of Sathan, the lure of the Deuill, than the ſage aduiſe, and wholſome councell of ſo mercifull a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, he (I ſay) than did open the déepe and hid treaſures of his manifold mercies, and did yet once againe ſhewe vs the gracious fauour of his louing countenance, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing euen then at the fall of our olde father Adam, that his onely ſonne Chriſt Ieſus ſhoulde deſcende from his celeſtiall throne and ſeate of maieſtie, and take the nature of a man vpon him, and ſhould breake the heade of the Serpent, that is, he ſhoulde daunt the power of the Deuill, valiauntly vanquiſhe the hoſt of Sathan, puyſſantly conquere the campe and companie of our enimies, ouerthrow the kingdome of bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Belzebub, breake downe the gates of the nethermoſt hell, and beate downe the walles of the Deuill his defenſed Caſtle, and deliuer vs poore afflicted people from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27972:9"/>
the cruell rage, and violent clauſe and tearing téeth of oure deuouring enimye. This was perfourmed at the fulneſſe of tyme, in the latter dayes, when God ſent his Aungell to the moſt happie, holye, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, and pure Virgin, who being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed with the ſpirit of the moſt high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, brought forth Chriſt Ieſus, our onely Sauiour, our onely redéemer, our onely ſuccour, ſafegarde, and defence, our ſure and ſtedfaſt rocke, our ſtable and conſtant hope, the rampire and caſtle of our helth, the ſoueraigne ſalue of our heauie and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull heartes, the ſole and ſingular, and moſte holſome remedie for all our diſeaſes. In this caſe therefore, we muſt doe our diligent indeuour, that we maye applye this playſter to oure gréeuous wounde, and ſo fruitfully enioy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of the ſame. For lyke as a great and infinite treaſure, lying hydde in the earth, will not enrich vs, vnleſſe with labour, care, and diligence we digge vp the ſame, and like as a great, ſwift, and couragious courſer, will nothing profite vs in flying from our enimies, vnleſſe we
<pb facs="tcp:27972:10"/>
learne how to ſit faſt vpon him, and ſo to eſcape, and as the ſurpaſſing knowledge, cunning, and ſcience of a learned, and well experienced phiſitian, will not helpe to cure our maladie and ſickneſſe, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our health and ſafetie, vnleſſe we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our diſeaſe vnto him, and deſire hys ayde, comfort, and aſſiſtaunce: euen ſo the meruellous mercies, the manifolde me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, and incomparable deſertes, the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting goodneſſe, and bountious liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the riches and excellent greatneſſe of the ineſtimable grace of God, through our ſwéete Sauiour graunted vnto vs, wyll not cure our diſeaſe, will not inlarge the boundes of our libertie, will not deliuer vs from the bondes and chaines of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, wherewith we are clogged, wyll not enrich vs with the glorious giftes, and precious pearles of iuſtice, holineſſe, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, and purity, vnleſſe we with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearts, with thankefull mindes, with heauie chéere, with hart oppreſſed, wyth greeuous grones, lamenting our former iniquities, confeſſing our manifolde miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes, deteſting all impietie, crauing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27972:10"/>
for our committed blaſphemie, and hartily ſorowing for our accuſtomed ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, ſtubburneſſe, and wilfull diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, doe diſplay our miſerie, and open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him our ſhamefull nakedneſſe, and in the bowelles of Ieſus Chriſt, in whome he is well pleaſed, deſire him with conſtaunt faith, with certaine hope, with earneſt and continuall prayer, to haue mercy vpon vs, to illuminate our hartes with the ſpirite of knowledge, to ſcoure away the clowdes of ignoraunce, to waſh away the ſpottes of ſinfull diſobedience, to kindle in vs a feruent, heauenly, true, burning, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charitie, and to worke in our hartes a continuall deſire alwayes to fulfill hys moſt bleſſed will, and therewith all to giue vs the power of his holye ſpirite to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame, to the glorie of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall maieſtie, the comfort of the godly, the fruitfull edification of our brethren, and the ſaluation of our owne ſelues, &amp; ſoules for euer and euer, in his glorious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:27972:11"/>
               <head>The meane, and way how to come to our heauenly father, with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Authour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate of prayer, and a diuiſion of hys worke. <hi>The thirde Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF we will therefore be the ſonnes of God, if we will be pertakers of thoſe infinite and celeſtiall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, which were gotten and purchaſed by the moſt pure bloude of the immaculate Lambe, if we will be healed by the ſwéete ſalue of his bloudy wounds, we muſt not ſlacke to runne vnto God our heauenly father, with continuall and heartie prayer. Which prayer bicauſe it is a thing ſo neceſſarie for chriſtians, that without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame we cannot attaine to the grace of God, and merites of our ſauiour Chriſt, and ſeing that daylye experience doth apparauntly, but pitifully teach vs, that in theſe oure dayes it is an exerciſe that is nothing at all, or verie lightly vſed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27972:11"/>
of many which beare the name of Chriſt, but in déede are not chriſtians. I meane and minde by the aſſiſtance of almightie God, and ayde of his holy ſpirit,<note place="margin">The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the Author.</note> to intreate ſomething of the ſame, I ſaye, of prayer: that the prowd contempt of the diſdainfull Epicures, which paſſe not for prayer, may be ſomething abated and diminiſhed, that the licentious life of beaſtly belly Gods, which take al their delite in worldly filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, may by the terrour of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be corrected and amended, that the rareleſſe concupiſence of worldly wicked men, which wallow in welth and worldly banities, maye by the knowledge of the bounden dueties be cut off, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that ſuch as be deceiued by ſimplicitie may be reformed, that ſuch as knowe not how to praye ſo, that they may mercifully be hearde, may charitably be inſtructed, that ſuch as are alreadie forwarde in the ſame, may thervnto be the more incenſed.<note place="margin">Tomo. <hi>5.</hi> lib. De preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</note> For Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is as the roote and foundation of al ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. For as the foundation doth make a ſhippe or houſe to be ſtrong, and holdeth
<pb facs="tcp:27972:12"/>
it, that it may not be diſſolued: ſo the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of prayer doth holde our lyfe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it ſtrong on all partes, and ſo, that without this no good can happen vnto vs, nor anye thing, which belongeth to our health. I will therefore that I may the more orderly procéede, diuide my whole talke into thrée principall partes, and firſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> by the grace of God, I will declare that if we doe reiect, or nothing regarde earneſt, and hartie prayer, that we be in preſent daunger of eternall damnation. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that if with pure prayer, we doe as we ought, call vpon God in Ieſus Chriſt our bleſſed ſauiour, for the aſſiſtaunce of hys holy ſpirite, we ſhall be ſure of moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, bliſſefull, &amp; immortall ſaluation, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> thirdlye, God guiding me, I will ſhewe plainely how we may praye ſo, that aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly we ſhall obtaine our requeſt. For although, the ſingular goodneſſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible mercies of almightie God, our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing father, cannot allure vs, the terrible vengeaunce, which he poureth downe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtifnecked ſinners, maye perchaunce conſtraine vs, to accompliſh that, which of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27972:12"/>
dutye we ſhoulde performe. Then when by continuall feare, of grieuous plagues and puniſhmentes, we are driuen from former negligence, to néedefull and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diligence, when by terrour of ſeuere iuſtice, the rayne of our loſe libertie is drawen in more ſtraightlye, ſo that we may not runne lyke royſting rouers at randome, to the heauie diſpleaſure of our almightie iudge, as willingly we woulde, and vnwiſely were wont, it may he, that the conſtaunt hope of ſo bountifull a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, ſo princely pearles, and ſurpaſſing a benifite, as is eternall ſaluation, maye prouoke and entiſe our appetite to ſhewe ſome earneſt zeale, and heartie deſire to pleaſe and ſerue our maker. Afterwards leaſt ſome ſimple, rude, &amp; ignoraunt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as many there be (the more it is to be lamented) ſhoulde perſwade themſelues, that they ſerue God well by prayer, when they deface his glory by ſome of their own ſuperſtitious inuentions, or popiſhe Ipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, it will not be farre from our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, briefly to proſecute the nature of true prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:27972:13"/>
               <head>That ſuch as neglect prayer, be in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of hell fire, the firſt part of the Authors diuiſion, which is continued vnto the .18. Chapter. <hi>The fourth Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt firſt I haue to proue, that ſuch, as neglect the exerciſe of praier, are in daunger of hell fire. And that plainely appeareth, bicauſe they flatly breake the commaundement of god, and wickedlye contemne the councell of Chriſt our ſauiour. They depriue God of his honour, and worſhip, they are trées, which beare no fruite, they are voyde of faith, hope, and truſt in Gods mercy. That they contemptuouſly diſpiſe the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God and Chriſt our ſauiour, it is euident. For the princely Prophet in the perſon of God ſaith, and flatlye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth on this ſorte: <hi>Inuoca me in die tribulationis, &amp; eruam te, &amp; glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficabis me,</hi> that is, call vpon me in the day of trouble, and I will deliuer thée, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27972:13"/>
thou ſhalt glorifie me, And Chriſt our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour chargeth vs on this maner: <hi>O rate ne intretis in tentationem.</hi> And ſainct Paule repleniſhed with the holye ghoſt, writeth thus. <hi>Inſtate deprecatione, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantes in ea cum gratiarum actione.</hi> Pray earneſtly, and continually watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there with all, and giuing thankes. And againe, Chriſt ſayth. <hi>Petite, &amp; acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietis, quaerite, &amp; inuenietis, pulſate, &amp; aperietur vobis.</hi> Aſke, and you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue, ſeeke, and you ſhall finde, knocke, and it ſhall be opened vnto you. And I will deſtroy (ſayth the Lorde in the firſt of <hi>Sophonie</hi>) the men that haue not ſought after the Lorde of Iacob. Such infinite places there are to be founde in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which plainely teſtifie vnto vs, that God ſtraightlye commaundeth vs to call vpon him, and threatneth deſtruction to ſuch as ſéeke him not. Nowe therefore ſuch as doe not take this meanes, which God hath prouided to come vnto him, muſt needs incurre the diſpleaſure of him. And alas howe are we able to withſtande the ſeuere iudgement of ſo mightie a god?
<pb facs="tcp:27972:14"/>
why doe we not tremble and quake to ſee our ſelues in ſo great a grieuous dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for as Paule ſayth, it is a terrible thing, to fall into the handes of the lyuing Lord. Who ſhall deliuer vs from the torments, that he ſhall cruciate, and torment vs withal? Who ſhal ſaue vs, if he condemn vs? Who ſhall bleſſe vs, if he curſe vs? Who ſhall reſtore vs to any life, if he doe lay vpon vs moſt bitter death? Deſperate is the eſtate of ſuch, as will not call vpon him, and they vndoubtedly can looke for nothing elſe, but extréeme, and cruell pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. For euen as a Prince here vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, if he take a fellone, which hath tranſgreſſed the lawes, diſturbed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, diſquieted good and godlye ſubiectes, violated his faith, diſpiſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and vilanouſly committed trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt his liedge, &amp; ſoueraigne Lord, if to ſuch a one, he of his frée goodneſſe, gentle moderation, and mercy, do graunt ſo much fauour, that if he giue vp a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication vnto his maieſtie, he will graunt him pardon, for his committed crimes, &amp; hainous offences, and then the rebellious
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27972:14"/>
tranſgreſſour of the lawes, eyther thorow negligence or contempt, doe refuſe ſo gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle an offer, will neuer let him eſcape without greeuous, horrible, and dreadfull tormentes: ſo God, prince of all princes, and Lorde of Lordes, whoſe mightie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie we vnthankefull creatures haue not duely reuerenced, whoſe name wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily we haue not glorified, whoſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prayſe we haue not magnified, whoſe iuſtice, we haue not feared, whoſe fatherly mercies we haue not imbraced, whoſe commaundementes we haue contemned, whoſe fearefull iudgementes we haue not regarded, whoſe decrées, and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we haue neglected, whoſe counſels we haue caſt off, and vngratfully refuſed, whoſe burning wrath, and hote indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we haue deſerued, if we doe reiect his fatherly goodneſſe, and tender care where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he doth call vs vnto him againe by prayer, and ſupplication, through his dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued ſonne, Chriſt Ieſus, our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and ſtill continue wilfull, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in our olde cankred, and hatefull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, will vndoubtedly caſt vs head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb facs="tcp:27972:15"/>
into vtter darckeneſſe, and painefull pangues and bitter anguiſh, with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and his curſed Aungels. For as he is gentle, ſo is he iuſt, as he is amiable, ſo is he terrible, as he is mercifull, ſo is hée wrathfull, to the humble, and penitente, he is a milde, and fauourable comforter, to the ſtifnecked, and diſobedient, he is an yrefull reuenger, to the true chriſtians, a preſent reliefe in daunger, to diſdainefull hypocrites, a conſuming fire, to poore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and oppreſſed Abels, a chéerfull, and faithfull friende, to perſecuting Cainites, an open enimy, to his ſéely ſhéepe, a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhephearde, to rauening Wolues, a ramping Lion, to ſimple ſoules, a coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious capitaine, to diſceitfull Deuils, a perpetuall torment, to faithfull people, a ſure defence, to tering Tigres, a deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring aduerſarie. For in his wrath, he will conſume his enimies, and in his fury, will confounde all his rebellious aduerſaries. Therefore Dauid ſayth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2.</note> ſerue the Lorde with feare, and reioyce vnto him with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence. Kiſſe the ſonne, leaſt he be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grye, and ſo ye periſh from the right way.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27972:15"/>
If his wrath be kindled, yea, but a litle, bleſſed are al they, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> put their truſt in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The dreadfull ende of them, againſt whome Gods wrath is kindled, and the daunger of the contempt of gods grace. <hi>The fift Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Prophet here knewe the dreadfull ende of thoſe againſt whome the wrath of God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed, and theyre of God infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, he, I ſay, knewe to what pitious eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, what lamentable, &amp; miſerable ende, what horrible condition they ſhould come to at the laſt. Therefore, he accounteth them bleſſed, holy, heauenly, happie, that put their truſt in the Lord, that ſerue him with feare, that worſhippe him, that obey the commaundementes of his diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, with iuſt reuerence.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 16.</note> For in the ſixtene of numbers, we may ſome thing perceiue how God will puniſhe contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous perſons, and rebellious deſpiſers of
<pb facs="tcp:27972:16"/>
his will and commaundement, where he maketh the earth to open hir mouth, and to ſwallowe vp <hi>Core, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> with their tentes, wiues, &amp; children, in the ſight of all the people of Iſrael, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they refuſed to come at the call of Moyſes, being a man as we are. What therefore ſhall he doe vnto vs, if we deſpiſe the commaundement giuen vs of hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo often repeated in the ſcriptures of purpoſe by the holy ghoſt, ſo conſtantlye confirmed by godly Prophetes, ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly declared by Chriſt himſelfe, hys dearely beloued ſonne, perfite God and man, which came downe from heauen to teach vs this leſſon: <hi>Quiſquis inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit nomen domini, ſaluus erit:</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall call vpon the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, he ſhall be ſafe. What ſhall he, I ſay, doe vnto vs in this caſe, if in that caſe, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the earth to ſwallowe them vp quicke, and cary them to hell? We may aſſuredly, vnleſſe with repentaunt hartes we call vpon him, looke for nothing elſe but vtter ruine, and confuſion, but eternall damnation, and immortall miſerie, but for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27972:16"/>
the terrible troubles, of tormented deuils, and moſt cruell ſtroakes of moſt heauie plagues. Let the deſperate eſtate of cruell and curſed Cain make vs beware, who woulde not after his hainous and bloudy fact, come to the throne of Gods mercye with teares, and lamentation, to bewayle his wickedneſſe, but miſtruſting the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodneſſe, and marueylous riches of the grace, and fauour of our mightie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and tender father, became abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable before the face of God, and a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble example to all ſuch, as contemne the great mercies of God, layde open to all them, that with humble, and ready minds, will thankfullye by prayer receiue them. Let the conſideration of vniuſt Iudas, who after he had betrayed Chriſt, the holy one of Iſrael, and vnſpotted lambe, which taketh away the ſinnes of the worlde, did hunge himſelfe, and woulde not take holde of the promiſes of God, but deſperatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired of the goodneſſe of him, among the companie of whoſe Apoſtles before he was numbred, ſtirre vs more feruently to runne to God in Chriſt our ſauiour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:27972:17"/>
diligence, with all continuaunce, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all certayne hope, and pure faith, in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, in prayer, and thankes gyuing. For if we doe, as did theſe miſerable men, not looke to be profred mercy, but refuſe the ſame, we ſhall be accounted breakers of the commaundements of God, diſpiſers of his worde, wicked workers of iniquity, and conſequentlye, worthy of the ſame moſt vnhappy reuengement, &amp; iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they were afflicted withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>An aunſwere to a captious cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, that might be layed to the Author. <hi>The ſixt Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt ſome perchaunce will ſay, that theſe two laſt examples doe not ſo much belong to negligence in prayer, as to an horrible terrour in their owne conſcience, conceyued for the cruell factes, they had committed. I aunſwere, that herein both may plainelye be perceyued. For that which in this place is moſt for my purpoſe, in theſe examples,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27972:17"/>
we ſée the iuſtice of God executed againſt them, that did violate his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by treaſon, murder, and falſhoode. Therefore death, and hell fire, is the guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and rewarde of ſuch as deſpiſe the will of God, and the will of God is, that we ſhoulde glorifie his name by pouring out our prayers vnto him. Againe, wée may eaſily ſée, that not onely deſperation, but alſo a will to committe theſe horrible crimes came through lacke of feruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and by a colde negligence in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, wherein they ſhoulde haue deſired in all there doings, the direction of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite, which if they had done, they had aſſuredly béene frée, both from the terrour of deſperation, and alſo from the guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſo miſchieuous vilanies. For ſaint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth: <hi>Siue quis virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis amore tenetur, ſiue quis ſtudet amplecti honorabilem coniugij caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniam, ſiue quis meditatur inijcere fraenum iracundiae, &amp; cum manſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine familiaritatem habere, ſiue quis putet ab inuidentiae lue purus eſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſi quis aliud quippiam facere ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:18"/>
quod ad rectè vniendum pertinet, duce precatione commodum, &amp; faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem habiturus eſt pietatis curſum.</hi> Whether a man be in loue with virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whether he indeuour to imbrace hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and chaſte matrimonie, whether he couite to bridle anger, and to be gentle or courtious, whether he wiſh to be cleane and pure from the peſtilent, and foule ſpot of enuie, or to conclude, if he deſire to doe any thing, whatſoeuer it be, that pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to good and godly life, by prayer hée ſhall eaſily, and commodiouſly attaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. The lacke therefore of feruentneſſe, and the daungerous negligence in praier, doth bring all wickedneſſe, vncleaneſſe, deſperation, murther, and all impietie. This therefore is the cauſe vndoubtedly, why in theſe moſt miſerable dayes of ours, both here, in the Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and almoſt throughout all the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the whole worlde, men runne hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into the pit of ignorance, and error, that they ſwarme togither to ſtirre vppe wilfull, and witleſſe warfare, that they ſwarne awaye from the ſtraight path of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27972:18"/>
chriſtian righteouſneſſe, that they ryfle in rancor, hatred, &amp; abhominable enmity, that they ſwel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the venimous poyſon of pride &amp; preſumption, that they with all endeuor plucke downe the golden pillers of godly peace, &amp; vnitie, that violently they breake the bands of heauenly concord, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they roote out the ſtampe of true religion, that they impugne the ſtate of holeſome veritie, that they darcken the bright, and ſhyning beames of chriſtian knowledge, &amp; clogge themſelues with the filthie fetters, of all abhominable outrage and iniquitie. But what? Doe we thinke, that the God of Iacob, and Lorde of Iſrael nowe at the laſt ſléepeth? Or do we think that he which neyther ſlumbreth, nor ſléepeth, now win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth at our wickedneſſe and wil not ſée it? Or do we thinke, that he, which deſtroyed afore time the people, that wrought wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe before his face, hath now chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his nature, and is no more diſpleaſed with blaſphemous behauiour? Or doe we thinke, that we are of habilitie to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande his furie, when he ſhall riſe vp to take vengeaunce vppon vs for our horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:27972:19"/>
vices daylie more and more increaſing amongſt vs? Or doe we thinke that we haue a ſpeciall priuiledge, and prerogatiue to doe what ſéemeth good in our fooliſhe fantaſies, and ydle braynes, without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection more than other haue had before? Or doe we thinke that the power is eyther dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, or his arme abridged, or his might impaired? Or doe we think, that he loueth vs more than he did his choſen charge, and peculiar people of Iſraell? Or can wée thinke ſo blaſphemouſly, that nowe he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth delite in our filthie doings, in wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton wils, and prowde pranckes, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hypocriſie? No no. Let vs not flatter our ſelues, nor dally with God, but let vs wiſely conſider, &amp; iuſtly ponder our looſe, and lewde liues, wherby we deſerue moſt ſharpe plagues, and puniſhmentes, moſt heauy, &amp; haſty reuengement, moſt ſeuere, and rigorous iudgement, &amp; let vs knowe, that the paſſing pacience, and gentle ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce of God, our heauenly Father, doth allure vs to ſpéedie repentaunce, to continuall care, yea to hearecloth, and aſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that ſo we may yéelde vnto his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27972:19"/>
for a pleaſaunt, and ſwéete ſacrifice, the bewtifull buddes of dutiful obedience. And let vs well conſider the mighty wrath of God nowe long ago ſet on fire againſt vs, and therewithall knowe that he ſlée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not, although he ſuſtaine vs, that he wincketh not, although he woontedly doe warne vs, and that he is not pleaſed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to proue vs by gentleneſſe, hys plagues be ſomething ceaſed, nor that we can abide his diſpleaſure burſting out, like a deuouring tempeſt, although he for hys mercie ſake doe abide paciently for our returne, nor that we be priuiledged, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed to vſe the workes of darkeneſſe, which onely belong to the ſonnes of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall darkeneſſe, although we by long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce be mercifully borne withall, nor that the ſtretched out arme of God is any thing abridged, although the violent force of his valyaunt power be nothing in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing as yet extended, or exerciſed, nor that he deliteth in our diſordred appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, although as yet he doe not poure preſent deſtruction vpon our heades, nor that he holdeth vs more deare, than he did
<pb facs="tcp:27972:20"/>
his choſen people, &amp; proper poſſeſſion, the houſe of Iſrael, although he more ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did execute iudgement vpon them than vpon vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>That if God ſpared not the Iewes, his peculiar people, he will not ſpare vs, baſtardely engraffed in hym. <hi>The ſeuenth Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr howe is it poſſible that wée which are but the braunches of wylde Oliues, ſhoulde receyue more fauour, force, or nouriſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the true, and natural Olyue trée, than the naturall ſprowtes, buddes, and braunches of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? the Iſraelites were, as though it were engraffed in the ſwéete graces, and tender mercies of almightie God, watred with the holeſome ſhowres of heauenly clemencie, nouriſhed with the fruitful fatneſſe of the ſoyle, wherein they were planted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, of Chriſt Ieſus. They were a nation euen by the choyſe of God himſelfe, ſeperated from all foreine, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27972:20"/>
ſtraunge people, for whoſe ſake he ſhewed manye wonderfull, and mightie miracles in the lande of Egypt, and afterwardes they were fedde miraculouſlye with the foode of Aungels, they receyued to their comfort the cleare ſtreames of moſt freſh and holeſome waters, flowing from the flintie ſtones, and craggy rockes in the daungerous deſert, with many ſuch like things, which did argue moſt manifeſtly the riches of Gods mercie towarde them. Yet for all this, when they rebelliouſly did murmure againſt God in the wilderneſſe, when they diſpiſed his ſeruaunt Moyſes, and grudged at his commaundements, he ouerthrewe them in the deſert, he plagued them moſt horriblye, ſending firie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents amongſt them, he perſecuted them vnto the death, and pyttifully deſtroyed them. How much more therefore ſhall he put vs out of the booke of lyfe, and cut vs from the ſtocke, vpon the which we were contrarie to nature, as wylde Oliues, ſet, and planted, if we doe not preuent his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with hartie, ſincere, and humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, if we doe not appeale to his mercy
<pb facs="tcp:27972:21"/>
ſeate by conſtant, certaine, and truſtie faith, if we doe not ſpéedily returne vnto him with a faythfull endeuour, neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to reuolt from him by lewde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, or vnchriſtian cogitation? How can it be, that he which is the Fountayne of all iuſtice, ſhoulde anye longer protect the deuilliſh impes of Antichriſt, ſpotted, and defiled wyth all iniuſtice, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he, which cannot be pleaſed with any thing, which ſauoureth of any corruption, ſhoulde any longer couer our curſed abhomination, and execrable impietie? O the deepe daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, wherewith we are compaſſed. O the piteous, eſtate through which we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daungered. O the profounde pitte of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whervnto we are plunged. If thus we moſt miſerable, and wofull wretches, wickedly continue without remorſe of conſcience, if we thus ragingly doe runne forwarde into vice, and vilanie wythout recourſe, if we thus obſtinately doe perſiſt in our péeuiſhe purpoſes, and peſtiferous inuentions, without remembraunce of our eſtate and calling, death ſhall deuour vs, horror ſhall holde vs, terror ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27972:21"/>
vs, confuſion ſhall ouerwhelme vs, bitter anguiſhe ſhall oppreſſe vs, ſinne ſhall ſubuert vs, ſorow ſhall ſhake vs, the iuſtice, and iudgement of God ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume vs, cruell enimies ſhall inuade vs, ſhame ſhall ſhadowe vs, terrible torments ſhall entrap vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre of Gods vengeance ſhall burne vs vp in the twinckling of an eye, and the paynes of hell ſhall plunge vs into moſt deſperate, and deadly dolors. In time therfore dearely beloued Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and naturall Countrie men, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the long ſuffering of God calleth vs vnto repentaunce. For God would not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould turne from his wickedneſſe &amp; lyue. He is a God, that deliteth in mercie, that dealeth friendly with the friendleſſe, that ſuccoureth the ſimple, that wiſheth the welth of the wounded, that comforteth the clogged conſcience, that breaketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bonds of the impriſoned ſoule, and heauie minde a ſunder, that fauoureth the fettred féete of his choſen ſeruants, that plucketh out the poore out of the pit of penurie, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them in the pleaſaunt paſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteſome
<pb facs="tcp:27972:22"/>
Paradiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>A repeating of the purpoſe of the fourth Chapter, that is, of the daunger of them that neglect prayer. <hi>The eyght Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt let vs returne to our former purpoſe, and proue that they be in daunger of eternall damnation, that deſpiſe and neglect the godlye exerciſe of prayer, which hereby is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that thereby they depriue God of his due honor and worſhip. For the worſhip of God, is nothing elſe, but a religious worke commaunded of God, and offered of vs by fayth to him to the ſetting forth, and celebration of his glorious, &amp; renowmed maieſtie. And as it appeareth by my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſcourſe, God hath commaunded this kinde of adoration, when he ſayth. <hi>Inuoca me in die tribulationis:</hi> call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me in the daye of trouble. And againe, when Chriſt ſayth: <hi>petite, pulſate, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,</hi> aſke, knock, ſéeke, and, <hi>orate ne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tretis
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27972:22"/>
in tentationem:</hi> praye leaſt you fall into temptation. And oftentimes we heare the like ſpoken to the ſame purpoſe. It is a worke therfore by him commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And moreouer, we may well perceiue that nothing can more pertaine to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious praiſe of God almightie, than to looke downe from the throne of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly maieſtie vpon poore afflicted people, hanging onely vppon the hope of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodneſſe, and accuſtomed mercy, and to relieue them, that haue nothing elſe to ſtick vnto, as ayde, and comfort, but hys gracious, good, and gentle fauour, wherby they may be deliuered from the tirannous rage, and more than beaſtly crueltie, of their ſauage, and ſworne enimies. For what made the glorious name of the God of Iacob ſo much to be redoubted amongſt all nations, as did his vnſpeakable mercy, wherwith he viſited the children of Iſrael, whan they were oppreſſed of the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Egyptians. He heard their grones, their heartie prayers pierced the miſtie clowdes, and came before his preſence, they aſcended into the eares of his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:27972:23"/>
maieſtie, their heauie griefes, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſorrowes were not hid from his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but obtayned moſt iuſt reuenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the blinde, and obſtinate E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians, whereby his name was moſt manifeſtly glorified. For many times he plagued with moſt ſharpe puniſhment the whole lande of Egypt for their ſakes, with Frogs, Graſhoppers, Caterpillers, death, and deſtruction of the firſt borne, and ſuch like, and at the laſt ouerwhelmed all their chiualrie with the bluſtring ſtormes, and roring rage of the red Sea. The due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and circumſpect animaduerſion of thys onely hyſtorie will doubtleſſe to euerie chriſtian man, ledde with the ſpirite of God, and numbred amongſt the elect veſſels of ſaluation, ſufficiently expreſſe the notable efficacie of prayer, on both partes, firſt both to vnderſtande the force in preuayling with God, and alſo the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious renoume of the Lorde his eternall maieſtie, through graunting the requeſt of his poore people. For when his people, the children of Iſrael, were after much affliction, trouble, and torment, delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27972:23"/>
out of the lande of Egypt, and was going into the wylderneſſe to ſerue the Lord their God, Pharao, and all his hoſte, perſecuted them in all haſte, to bring them againe into bondage, which would haue bene more grieuous, and ſorrowfull, than preſent death vnto them. And when they were in ſuch caſe that preſently before their faces was the red foming, and ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Seas, vpon their right handes high, ſteepe, and craggie mountaynes, vpon the which they could not aſcend, and eſcape, vpon their left hande no refuge, but daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and deadly perilles, behinde their backes, their cruell, diſdainefull, wicked, and horrible enimies, threatning death, tormentes, and perpetuall miſerie: then they cried vnto the Lorde in their miſerie, &amp; he deliuered them out of their diſtreſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.</note> they poured out their complaintes before him, and he glorified himſelfe by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueraunce, they humbly ſought for his gracious aſſiſtaunce, and he mercifullye graunted the requeſt of their earneſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, they feared bondage, he gaue them libertie, they were compaſſed with grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb facs="tcp:27972:24"/>
daungers, he gaue them ſure, are ſafe paſſage, they were ready to be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the ſworde, he ouerthrew their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they were almoſt perſecuted vnto death, he brought to paſſe that they ſawe the death, and deſtruction of there perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting tyrannes. But how did he deliuer them? Certes he commaunded the wylde waters to ſtaye their courſe, to loſe their ſwiftneſſe, to chaunge their nature. He made the waltring waues to be turned into ſtrong walles, the ſurging ſeas into the vſe of ſturdy ſtones, the flickring floods into a ſteady bridge, ſo that his people paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer with eaſe, &amp; ſafetie. But when the Egyptians were ſo bolde, to enter into the ſame paſſage, they were ouerwhelmed in the waters, the walles turning, and chaunging themſelues into their woonted nature. Thus was his glorie magnified, his name glorified, his power knowne, his mercie ſpecified, his terror taught, his loue enlarged, his might multiplied, his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe graffed in the heartes of his people, that afterwards they loued him as a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full father, they feared him as a mightie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27972:24"/>
reuenger, they honored him, as a péereleſſe Prince, they reuerenced him, as a ſeuere iudge, they glorified him, as their onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerer, they ſanctified him as their holye profectour, they folowed him, as a well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Capitaine, they obeyed his will, as their only guide, and defender. For his name to them was fauourable, to other nations, and people terrible, to them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, to gentiles fearefull, to them peaceable, to others dreadfull, to them it brought quietneſſe and ſafetie, to others confuſion, to them tranquilitie, to others miſerie, to them plenteouſneſſe of all thinges, to other penurie of things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, to them ſolace, to forrein kingdomes ruine, and ouerthrowe, to them pleaſure, to other plagues, to them a ioyfull expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of mercie, to others an horrible ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of extreme iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Nothing apperteyneth more to the glorie of God than prayer. <hi>The ninth Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27972:25"/>WHat therefore can more belong to the eſtabliſhing of his prayſe, to his royall pompe, to the blaſt of his magnificence, through all the earth, to the publiſhing of his glorious name, than with humble, and hartie pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers continually to be called vpon, of hys afflicted people, that he may ſtretche out his arme, and declare his power, &amp; bende his bowe, and valiauntly ouerthrow his enimies? Verily nothing. For thus he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſimple captyues, and bindeth the bloudy Balaamites, he ſaueth his ſiely ſouldiours, &amp; ſpoyleth the boaſting bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuckers, he protecteth his poore people, and racketh vnruly ribaldes, he mightilye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde all hope helpeth the miſerable, and contrariwiſe, debaſeth, ſubuerteth, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeth the bragging boldnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proude diſdainefull, and ſwelling tirannes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore that it is a religious worke commaunded by God himſelf, enioyned to vs by Chriſt our onely ſauiour, taught by the Apoſtles, and Prophets, tending to the celebration, &amp; propagation of his eternall glorie, renowme, and reuerence, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27972:25"/>
more by ſubduyng the ſtubborne, ſinfull, &amp; malicious people, and by relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, helping, and ſuccouring, his afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, humble, and ſily flocke, it muſt néedes folowe, that they which diſpiſe the vſe of prayer, and negligently, nay rather, obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, and deuiliſhly contemne the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, and promiſes of God, our heauenly father, and nothing regarde his gentle admonition, calling them by paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to hartie repentaunce, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of wicked life, that they, I ſaye, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue God of his due honour, ſpoyle him of his worſhip, rob him of his reuerence, and conſequently, fall into the daunger of eternall damnation. For 4. <hi>Iohan. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tales quaerit, qui adorant illum.</hi> The father ſéeketh ſuch, as worſhip hym, not ſuch as renounce his lawes, and reiect his commaundementes. And his not ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is nothing elſe, but miſery, griefe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, and condemnation. Againe, they are trées which beare no fruit. For they which are not poſſeſſed with the ſpirite of God, which are not directed with his holy hand, which are not illuminate with the light of
<pb facs="tcp:27972:26"/>
heauen, which are not aſſiſted with the helpe of the higheſt, nor ſtirred vp with the motion of the holy ghoſt, nor plentifullye enriched with the graces of Chriſt our ſauiour, cannot bycauſe of their weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, will not bycauſe of their wilfull wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, neyther doe couite bycauſe of their fraile, and curſed corruption, eyther to deliuer themſelues from the chaine of Sathan, wherewith they are bounde and tyed, or to repleniſh themſelues wyth the ſwéete, and well ſauering flowers of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that they maye be purified, to the proofe wherof, Chriſt ſayth. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15. <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a ſine me nihil poteſtis facere,</hi> bycauſe without me ye can doe nothing. And <hi>Math.</hi> 15. <hi>Omnis plantatio, quam non plantauit pater meus caeleſtis, eradica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur,</hi> euery planting, which my heauenly father hath not planted, ſhal be rooted out. And <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15. <hi>Si quis in me non manſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, eiectus eſt foras, ſicut palmes. &amp;c.</hi> If anye man doth not abide in me, he is caſt out, as a braunche, and withereth, and they gather it, and caſt it into the fyre, and burne it. Here we maye perceyue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27972:26"/>
that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are not directed with the ſpirit of God, are not the ſonnes of God, but impes of Antichriſt, not the friendes of God, but the limmes of the Deuill, not ſwallowers of ſaluation, but heires of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall condemnation. And ſaint Paule ſayth. <hi>Filij dei ſunt, qui ſpirit u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur.</hi> They are the ſonnes of God, which are driuen by the ſpirite of God. And Chriſt ſayth in the, 15. of Iohn. <hi>Ques meae vocem meam audiunt.</hi> My ſhéepe heare my voyce, and his voyce is. <hi>Luc.</hi> 15 <hi>Quod oportet ſemper orare, nec defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigari.</hi> That we muſt alway praye, and neuer be wearie. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſirt of <hi>Mathew</hi> he preſcribeth forme of prayer, ſaying. <hi>Ad hunc ergo modum orate vos. Pator noſter. &amp;c.</hi> Praye ye after this maner. Our father, and ſo forth. But they which contemne prayer, will neyther alwayes pray, which Chriſt commaundeth, nor vſe the forme of prayer, which Chriſt preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, nor leaue the lewdeneſſe, which God abhorreth. How therefore can they be any thing elſe but trées without fruite, clouds without water, rotten rootes without life,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:27"/>
barren grounde without corne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>les without curnels, and vnprofitable barke without ſappe, or ſauour. For like as the vine braunch can bring forth no fruite, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it remaine ſtill in the vine, euen ſo we can bring forth no goodneſſe, vnleſſe we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in Chriſt. And how is it poſſible, that they which heare Chriſt commaunde, and will not obey, that heare the ſhepchearde of their ſoules cal, and will not follow, that heare the ſauiour of the worlde counſell them for there ſafetie, helth, and welfeare, and will not attende, that they ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue any commoditie, ioy, ſolace, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, to refreſhe their lingring, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing ſoules, almoſt, or elſe altogither pined awaye for lacke of good nouriſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>That God reſpecteth them, that call vpon him, and reiecteth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, wyth the diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities thereof. <hi>The tenth Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:27972:27"/>EVerye good, and perfite gift, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from aboue from the father of light, who beſtoweth his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſure wythout ſparing reſtraint, vpon all them, that with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, and humble, and hartie requeſt ſhall deſire in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, hys grace, fauour, and euerlaſting goodneſſe. But from ſuch, as before Gods goodneſſe preferre there fooliſhe fantaſies, and ſéeke rather to pleaſe themſelues in worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, then to pleaſure themſelues with the worde of lyfe, he worthily taketh away his grace, forſaketh them vtterlye, leaueth them deſtitute, wil no more ſée vnto them, in ſo much, that through his abſence, and departure, there miſerable minde is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with pernicious errours, their ſenſes darkned, their vnderſtanding ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured, their reaſon oppreſſed, their wyll impriſoned, their hartes encombred, their heades enraged, their deuiſes ouerturned, their purpoſes diſapoynted, their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors hindred, their intentes diſordred, their trouble augmented, their anguiſh exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, their ſorrowe doubled, their griefe
<pb facs="tcp:27972:28"/>
more bitterly ſharpned, their ſtrength ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, their life almoſt deuoured, then ſpirites ſcattered, their dolours ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ewed, their wyt waſted, their wiſdome confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, their learning ſubuerted, their policy diſturbed, their counſelles aboliſhed, their bodies weakened; their ſoules endaunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, their thoughts defiled, their fayth po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, their pietie defaced, their rage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brideled, their furie enflamed, their wrath incenſed, and all vicious, and deteſtable impietie, ſlaunder, and vylanie beyonde meaſure encreaſed. For the corruption of our mortall, fraile, and inconſtaunt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is readie without reaſon to reuenge iniurie, vnleſſe religion doe reſtraine it. The raging ſtormes of our fleſhly mindes are woont to burſt out into daungerous attempts, vnleſſe the holeſome counſell of the ſacred ſcriptures be receiued. The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton will of a waywarde veſſell of iniquitie maye lightly be toſſed into the perilous floudes of yrefull indignation, and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie diſpleaſure, vnleſſe it ſayle in the ſafe ſhip, and vnbroken Barcke of Gods infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite grace, and mercy. The olde, and feſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27972:28"/>
wounde of cruell hate, and horrible eaſie, will, as it is woonted, eate vp, and conſume the ſounde partes of pacience, vnleſſe it be ſalued with the ſwéete Oyle of Gods holy ſpirite, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> filthie ruſt of popiſh ignoraunce will diſgrace, and deface the truth of ſincere religion, vnleſſe it be ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red awaye with the light of the gracious goſpell, the deadly dregges of humane traditions will daungerouſly corrupt the vertuous medicine of eccleſiaſticall doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, vnleſſe by the good aduiſe of ſome carefull, and ſkilfull Phiſitian they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, and caſt out, the contagious infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of noyſome, and vnhelthfull humore will in the minde of many men be cauſes of moſt grieuous, and bitter ſickneſſe, vnleſſe they by the circumſpect conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and diligent aduiſe of ſome godlye, learned, and well inſtructed chriſtian be auoyded, purged, and wiſely diſplaced, the peſtilent inuaſion of the créeping can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of humane confidence, wyll malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly infect the whole bodye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apparent, and viſible church of Chriſt, vnleſſe the playſter of Gods direction be fitly applied,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:29"/>
to the contynuall motions of mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and briefly, godlyneſſe, and all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will ſuffer moſt lamentable ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack in the troubleſome waues, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſeas of vayne fantaſies through the bluſtring windes, and terrible tempeſtes of deuiliſhe deſires, and raging appetites, vnleſſe Chriſt riſe vp, and commaunde the waters to be ſtill, the tempeſtes to ceaſe, the windes to be calme, the weather to be cléere, and the ſhip to be ſafe. Seing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſuch is the eſtate of men, which eſtéeme not, neyther regarde the goodneſſe of God, that of themſelues they can not helpe themſelues, nor by other meanes be preſerued in ſafetie, bicauſe nothyng can ſuccour him, whome God forſaketh, ſeing that nothing procéedeth out of the hart of man, vnleſſe it be ſauced with his mercy, grace, and bountie, but it is abhominable, and wicked before the face of almightie God, ſeing that the ffincking wéedes, and noyſome darnell of vices, wickedneſſe, and vngodlyneſſe, doe burſt out ſodainely, and in a moment when the ſéede of Gods holye worde is not ſowed in the hart of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27972:29"/>
man, and watred with the ſwéete ſhowres of heauenly mercie, ſeing that when God doth not extende his power, grace, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, nothing is pleaſaunt, fruitfull, or acceptable, but al things are ordered with vnruly rage, with bloudy beaſtlyneſſe, with diſordered confuſion, and horrible tempeſt of wicked, and witleſſe abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and againe, ſeing that they, which reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful exerciſe of prayer, can not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e directed by the finger, hand, or ſpirite of God, bicauſe they are not Gods children, becauſe they deſpiſe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, &amp; counſell, bicauſe they refuſe to heare his voyce, when he calleth them to continuall prayer, and earneſt repentaunce of their former liues, it muſt néedes folowe, that they are vnfruitefull trées, that is, rotten ſtockes, that bring forth no good, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt fruite, but withered, and infectious leaues, impoyſoned with venimous, and filthie contagion, and therfore ſhall be caſt into hell fyre, and condemned to eternall, bitter, and moſt horrible plagues, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes. For nowe the axe is layde to the roote of the trée, and euerye trée that
<pb facs="tcp:27972:30"/>
bringeth not forth good fruite, ſhall be cut downe, and caſt into the fyre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>What vertues they be voyde of, that pray not <hi>The .xi. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOreouer they lacke fayth, hope, and conſtant truſt, in the moſt precious bloude of our ſauioure Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore are in deſperate eſtate. For Chriſt ſaith: No man commeth to my father but by me, meaning that vnleſſe they put off their owne corruption, and ſhake off their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hypocriſie, cut away cleane from them the confidence in themſelues, or of other Idols, vnleſſe they confeſſe themſelues to be of themſelues wicked, diſceitful, weake, vnable, miſchieuous, and damnable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſurely beléeue that Chriſt came from his throne in heauen, and tooke the nature of man vpon him, to worke their righteouſneſſe, to appeaſe his fathers wrath, which was enflamed againſt all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27972:30"/>
ſinful, vngodly people, to deliuer them from the ſeruitude, and bondage of the Deuill, vnder whome they were ſubiect, and to ſet them at libertie with the raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and price of his moſt ſacred, and bleſſed bloud, which was poured out vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Croſſe, by cruell, and vnthankfull Iewes, meaning, I ſay, that vnleſſe hée beléeue this with ſtedfaſt faith, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the ſame preſent himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of God, firmely truſting that for Chriſtes ſake he ſhall be accepted, and mercifullye receyued, no man can come vnto the father of heauen, or enioy the gracious aſpect of the mightie God of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, but is vtterly deſtitute of the glory of God, and is a firebrande of hell, and heire of eternal miſery. And <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith: With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fayth it is vnpoſſible to pleaſe God. And againe: Whatſoeuer commeth not of fayth, is ſinne, and it is fayth that maketh a man to be ſaued. For Chriſt ſayth to a woman, that came vnto him. <hi>Fides tua te ſaluam fecit.</hi> Thy fayth hath made thée hole, which is to be vnderſtanded, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of bodily helth, but alſo of heauenly ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<pb facs="tcp:27972:31"/>
And againe, <hi>qui non credit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus eſt.</hi> He that doth not beleeue, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie iudged, or condemned. Therefore they, which doe diſpiſe, reiect, or contemne prayer, if they be vnfaythfull, are in moſt certaine peril, and danger of hell fire. But that they are vnfaithfull, it ſhall, by the aſſiſtance of almightie God, be declared by the force, fruits, and effectes of fayth. which bicauſe they are innumerable, and infinite, it is requiſite, that we ſpeake of a few only, which wil ſufficiently ſhew vnto vs, howe farre they abhorre from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent gifte, wherewith the dartes of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils be quenched, the hoſt of Antichriſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercommed, and the firie flames of Hell extinguiſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>That they lacke loue, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the ſpeciall fruites of fayth, which exerciſe not prayer. <hi>The .xij. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:27972:31"/>FAith, wherſoeuer it be, doth bring forth, or ingender repentaunce, doth apprehende the ſpirit of god, doth worke in mans harte loue, and obedience, which fruites, and effects, if they neceſſarilye porceede of faith, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after it ſhal appeare, ſée that by no meanes they may be ſeperated, and contrarilye, if they can neuer be founde in any of them, which deſpiſe prayer, as it ſhall be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it muſt néedes of neceſſitie folowe, they haue no fayth, but are dry, deade, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull, and faithleſſe people. But firſt let vs ſée whether repentaunce procéede of faith, or no, and then, whither ſuch men can be repentant. Faith when it is giuen from heauen, and placed in the heart of man, then it doth, as it were, rule, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne all the motions of the minde, it tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and prooueth, and ſercheth all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of his cogitations, it ſéeketh, &amp; ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, ſcoureth, and clenſeth away, the filth, the ruſt, the droſſe, the dregges of all impietie. For God, in the firſt of <hi>Eſay</hi> ſayth, if your ſinnes be as red as ſcarlet, I will make them as white as ſnowe,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:32"/>
which commeth onely by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> on, through which we appeare righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of our mightie God, and iuſtification commeth onely through faith in the moſt precious bloud of our onely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt. For <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith in the thirde chapter to the <hi>Romaines:</hi> The righteouſneſſe, or iuſtification no boubt, which is good before God, commeth by the fayth of Ieſus Chriſt vnto all, and vppon all, that beléeue. There is no difference. For all haue ſinned, and lacke the prayſe, that is of valure before God: but are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied fréelye by his grace, through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption which is in Chriſt Ieſu, whome God hath made a ſeate of mercy through fayth in his bloud, to ſhewe the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which before him is of valure, in that he forgyueth the ſinnes, that are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which God did ſuffer, to ſhewe at this time the righteouſneſſe, that is allowed of him, that he might be accounted iuſt, and iuſtifier of him, that beléeueth in Ieſus. Hitherto Paule. But vnleſſe the ſharpe ſalue of hartie repentaunce be layde vnto the feſtred woundes of our ſinfull hartes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27972:32"/>
it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpoſſible that they ſhoulde be purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, cleanſed, or healed. For therefore the ſcripture calleth vs ſo often to repentance. <hi>Conuertimini ad me &amp; ſaluieritis.</hi> Turne vnto me (ſayth the Lorde) and ye ſhall be ſafe, and againe: <hi>Si conuerſus fuerit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius. &amp;c.</hi> If the wicked ſhall turne from his euill way, and <hi>nolo mortem pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris,</hi> I will not the death of a ſinner, but that he repent and liue, and <hi>reſipiſcite, &amp; credite euangelio,</hi> repent, and beléeue the goſpell, and <hi>non veni vocare iuſtos, ſed peccatores ad penitentiam,</hi> I came not to call the iuſt, but ſinners to repentance. So that here we ſée plainely, that firſt is ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conuerſion to God, and repentaunce, then helth, or life, or ſafetie, whereby we may well perceyue, that vnleſſe repentaunce doe launch, and cut, and rent our hartes, we can not come to the perfection of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient chriſtians. And againe: An humble, and contrite heart is an acceptable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Lorde, to whome nothing is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, that procéedeth not of faith. For the Apoſtle ſayth: Whatſoeuer is not of fayth, is ſinne, and with ſinne howe can
<pb facs="tcp:27972:33"/>
God be pleaſed? It remayneth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>re that repentaunce, whereby the ſoule is ſorrowfully charged, but therewithall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall chéerefully be diſcharged, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred, and brought forth by fayth. For like as in a fielde, or garden, ſwéete, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt, or delectable flowers, can not grow freſhly, &amp; abundantly, before that wéedes, and ſtones, and thornes be raſed vp, and caſt out, euen ſo the moſt deliteſome fruit of dame vertues grace, can not plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repleniſhe the fielde, or garden of mans hart, vnleſſe firſt the briers of vices, and ſtones of wicked abhomination be by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce caſt out, and exiled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Zachaeus an example of an hartie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter, and that repentance is the ſalue to recure the wounds of wicked lyfe. <hi>The .xiij. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THerefore <hi>Zacheus,</hi> the prince of Publicanes in the .19. of <hi>Luke,</hi> when he had receyued the fayth of Chriſt, burſt out into theſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27972:33"/>
wordes and ſayde. <hi>Ecce Domine, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midium bonorum meorum do pauperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. &amp;c.</hi> Beholde Lorde, the halfe of my goodes I giue to the poore, and if I haue defrauded any man of any thing, I render to him foure folde, which wordes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly doe giue a moſt certayne token of heartie repentaunce. For he did ſo much deteſt his former iniquitie, ſo much lament his olde enormities, ſo willinglye condemne his practiſed prankes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull dealinges, that he not onelye did purpoſe in time to come to auoyde the lyke, but alſo did with moſt readie minde, recompence them foure folde, whome he had before deceiued, or oppreſſed. And in the ſeconde of the <hi>Actes,</hi> when diuers at the preaching of <hi>Peter</hi> began to beléeue, they being pricked in conſcience, exclamed on this ſorte. Yée men and brethren what ſhall we doe? here they knowing by the ſermons of the Apoſtle, that they hadde a long time erred from the truth, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued rather their owne inuentions, than the true God, and therefore perceyuing that they were in daunger of the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:34"/>
and terrible hate of the Lord hoſts deſired earneſtlye to knowe by what meanes they myght eſcape y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vengeance, being readie to fall on their heades, and ſorowfully lamented their dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. And Peter anſwereth with theſe words. <hi>Delictorum paenitentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agite. &amp;c.</hi> Repent your offences. Here we ſée y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſalue, wherwith their heauy harts, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with wickedneſſe, were firſt refreſhed, was hartie repentaunce, after they came to the faith of Chriſt Ieſus. The Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uits. 3. <hi>Ionae,</hi> beleeued God, &amp; commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a generall faſting, which did well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their remorſe of conſcience for their former contempt of Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and refuſall of his mercies, and tormenting of his Prophetes, whereby they turned away at the laſt the wrath of the Lord from themſelues, and their citie, all which doe proue, that where faith is, there is repentaunce. Nowe let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider a while whether true repentance may be found in them, that continue the vſe of prayer or no.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:27972:34"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſcription of repentaunce, and the partes therof, and the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the ſaued theefe. <hi>The .xiiij. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>REpentaunc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a true griefe, and ſorrow for the offence committed againſt GOD, wherewith the minde is oppreſt, the ſorrowfull hart moſt miſerably tormented the ſenſes troubled, the vnderſtanding ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the life afflicted, the woonted wanton ioyes altogither baniſhed, but ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant force of a liuely faith doth agayne reuiue the languiſhing ſpirit, with an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire, and conſtant aſſurance, hoping for frée pardon for the merites of Chriſt his paſſion, whereby is ingendered a full purpoſe neuer more to haunt the brothell houſes of ſinne, and iniquitie, but alwaies to liue in pure conuerſation, and ſincere pietie. Herein be principall, and eſpeciall partes, due contrition, and conſtant faith. Contrition maketh a man to tremble, and
<pb facs="tcp:27972:35"/>
quake, to conſider the violent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, incenſed againſt ſinne, wherewith he is brought into extreme feare, terror, and anguiſhe, and for that deteſteth the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble filthyneſſe, and deformitie of the ſame. And in ſuch caſe is it poſſible to ſtand, and not to deſire pardon? To require mercie? To craue deliuerance? To complaine our eſtate? To lament our miſeries? To ſeeke a ſalue? To procure an holeſome medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, whereby we may be reſtored to our helth? No no, and eſpecially, ſeing fayth, inſtilled into our hartes by the ſpirite of God, doth perſwade vs, that we ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, if we call, that we ſhall be raunſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if we require it, that we ſhall be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, if humbly with hartie prayers we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to the good Phiſition of the ſoule, Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and ſauiour. What madneſſe were it to thinke, that any man, being ſure of moſt miſerable tormentes, if he holde his peace, and is alreadie plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the deſperate conſideration of the ſame, and féeling their extreme bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and cruell ſharpneſſe, if on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie part, he were ſure to eſcape ſo great
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27972:35"/>
a daung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, ſo apparent a perill, ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous a miſerie, by opening his mouth, and deſiring mercie, that he woulde not with readie minde, with chéerefull hart, with all ſpéedie haſt, proſtrate himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudge, and in moſt lowly wiſe, and carefull humilitie beſéech him of his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goodneſſe, and deſired bountie, to dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him? The théefe which was hanged with Chriſt on his right hande, when he had receyued the boldneſſe of fayth, and therewith was brought to godlye repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, did deſire Chriſt moſt humbly to remember him, whan he came to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, &amp; euerlaſting kingdome. Ye he did not refuſe to call vpon him, but by calling was delyuered from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, from the mouth of hell, from the anguiſh of the ſoule, from the death eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, to which he had ſurely bene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, if he had deſpiſed, or not regarded the profite of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:27972:36"/>
               <head>The things that hinder the fruiteful exerciſe of praier, deſperation, and the contrarie thereof, that is, ſecuritie. <hi>The .xv. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat is it therefore, that hindreth a man, ſo that he doth not vſe the fruitefull exerciſe of prayers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Surely, eyther deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or elſe ſecuritie. Deſperation drowneth a man in deadly ſorrowes, in bitterneſſe of ſoule, in the furious floudes of moſt déepe and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitefull dolours. Therefore whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it is founde, it ſhutteth out cleane the force of fayth. But ſecuritie maketh a man careleſſe, hardneth his heart, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſtonie ſpirites, and cauſeth to cry, peace, peace, when deſtruction hangeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his heade. This alſo, when contrition is abſent, hath no parte or porcion in a faythfull heart. Whereof it foloweth, that true repentaunce, whereby the harts of chriſtians are regenerated, their willes chaunged, their mindes framed a newe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27972:36"/>
their deſires reformed, their liues amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, their cogitations cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed, their though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes purified, their ſpirite ſanctified, cannot be founde in thoſe, that doe not continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burſt out in moſt hartie prayers, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring grace, goodneſſe, pardon, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and conſequently, that ſuch are not faithfull, but faithleſſe, not fruitfull, but fruitleſſe, not gracious, but graceleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Secondly, faith doth apprehend the ſpirite of God. For Chriſt ſaith. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 7. If any man thirſt, let him come to me, and drinke. He that beleueth in me, as the ſcripture ſayth, ſhall haue floudes of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of lyfe flowing from his bellye, and this he ſpake of the ſpirite, which they, that beleue him, ſhould receyue. And <hi>ad Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſios.</hi> 1. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth: In whome (ſpeakyng of Chriſt) alſo ye after that, you had heard the worde of truth, I meane the goſpell of your ſaluation, wherein you beleue, were ſealed with the holye ſpirite of promiſe, which is the earneſt pledge of our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, to redéeme the purchaſed poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that vnto the lawde and glory of God. The ſpirite of God therefore doth
<pb facs="tcp:27972:37"/>
poſſeſſe the hartes of the faythfull. But let vs now conſequently conſider, whither i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be founde in ſuch, that will not feare God, which ſaint Paule ſéemeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, <hi>Romanes.</hi> 8. By theſe wordes. <hi>Non enim accepiſtis ſpiritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruitutis in timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſed accepiſtis ſpiritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adoptionis filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei, in quo clamamus, Abba pater. &amp;c.</hi> For ye haue not againe receyued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of bondage in feare, but ye haue receyued the ſpirit of adoption of the ſonnes of god, whereby we cry, <hi>Abba</hi> father. For that ſpirite doth teſtifie to our ſpirite, that we are the ſonnes of God, and in the fourth to the Galathians, bicauſe you are the ſonnes of God, God hath ſent the ſpirite of his ſonne into your harts, crying, <hi>Abba</hi> father. Here in theſe places, Paule doth manifeſtly ſhewe, that the ſpirite of God, when it reſteth in the hartes of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, doth ſo mollifie mans ſtony minde, ſo breake downe the brazen walles of ſléepie ſecuritie, ſo confounde the pernitious, and peſtilent purpoſes of negligent impietie, and agayne ſo comforteth the ſorrowfull ſoule, ſo refreſheth the weary wil, ſo repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27972:37"/>
and healeth the broken hart, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her by contempt of Gods wrath is proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, neyther by lacke of truſt, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, helth is togither baniſhed, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall prayer is poured out to God, as to a father, that with naturall, yea more then naturall affection, doth tender his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted children, his choſen veſſels, his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing friendes, which appéereth by crying in fayth <hi>Abba</hi> father. It is therefore proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that they which crie not with hartie affection vnto God our heauenlye father, haue not the ſpirite of God, &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they are reiected from the number of the ſaints, and ſonnes of God. Thirdly fayth worketh in mans hart loue, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. For that doth moſt perfitely paint out the tender mercies, the great good wil, the gracious fauour, the louing kindneſſe of God the father to man in creating him, of God the ſonne in raunſoming him, of God the holye ghoſt in directing him, in creating him, by making him of nothing a noble creature, in redéeming him, by making of a bonde ſeruant to the Deuill an adopted ſonne to himſelfe, in directing
<pb facs="tcp:27972:38"/>
him, by reſtrayning him from moſt abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable impietie, whether hée woulde runne, and caſt himſelfe headlong into pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent daunger, and kéeping him in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of his tender father, &amp; creator. Theſe with innumerable, and infinite commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties more, will mooue almoſt a ſenſeleſſe hart to contend with all endeuour to loue, to pleaſe, to folowe, to praiſe, to obey, to reuerence, to worſhip, and honour him by whome they are beſtowed, and giuen, and vndeſeruedly, fréely, bountifully, without reſpect of the receyuer his worthyneſſe, and onely for the giuers mercie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>The effects of fayth in Mari of Betha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, which is Marie Magdalene, with an enumeration of cauſes, why they bee condemned, which reiect prayer. <hi>The .xvi. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MArie of <hi>Bethania,</hi> after ſhée had receyued fayth, ſo loued Chriſt, that ſhe not onely was wylling
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27972:38"/>
to doe that which was commaunded in the lawe of God, but alſo exerciſed an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie meanes, whereby ſhée did ſhewe forth hir burning, and feruent loue towardes Chriſt. For when he was ſet at meate in a Pharyſeis houſe, ſhe brought an Alablaſter boxe of oyntment, and ſhée ſtoode at his féete behind him wéeping, and began to waſhe his féete with teares, and did wipe them with the heares of hir head, and kiſſed his féete, and annoynted them with oyntment, and Chriſt teſtifieth in the ſame place, the ſeuenth of Luke, that ſhe loued much. Chriſt alſo ſayth in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téenth of Iohn. If anye man loue mée, he will kéepe my ſaying, and againe, <hi>qui non diligit me, ſermones meos non ſeruat,</hi> he that doth not loue me, kéepeth not my ſaying, whereby it appeareth that fayth is not without the loue of God. The loue of God is not without obedience, obedience is not, where prayer is not exerciſed, as it is proued before. Therfore they which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne, or neglect, or doe not vſe contynuall prayer, are vnfaithful &amp; diſobedient rebels againſt God and his annoynted. Nowe
<pb facs="tcp:27972:39"/>
therefore ſéeing that for ſuch lacke of due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie on our partes, the holy, and heauenlye will of our eternall God is nothing regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the ſwéete, and holeſome counſell of Chriſt Ieſus, our mercifull, and mightie mediatour, wilfully condemned the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and promiſed mercy by the holye ghoſt, in ſcripture plentifullye declared, wickedly refuſed, ſeing that God is ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of his reuerence, depriued of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, robbed of his glorie, prayſe, and of our dutifull obedience, ſeing that they, which doe not exerciſe continuall prayer, are trées bearing no fruite, which are good for nothing, but to be cut downe, and caſt into the fire, ſeing that they are fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, deſperate, ſecure, fruitleſſe, and harde hearted hypocrites, truſting more to the fonde illuſions of their vaine fantaſies, than the riches of Gods eternall mercies, bathing themſelues in the ſincke of ſinne, and foule puddle of blaſphemous iniquity, it muſt néedes of neceſſitie folow, that they are burning firebrandes of hell, ſonnes of the Deuill, and heires of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For as the Prophet <hi>Nahum</hi> ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:27972:39"/>
firſt Chapter. <hi>Deus emulator, &amp; vlciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens dominus, vlciſcens dominus, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens furorem, vlciſcens dominus in hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſuos, &amp; iraſcens ipſe ſuis inimicis.</hi> God is a zelous, and a reuenging Lorde, a reuenging Lorde, and wrathfull, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging Lorde againſt his enimies, and angry againſt his aduerſaries. <hi>Ante fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem indignationis eius quis ſtabit, &amp; quis reſiſtet in ira furoris eius?</hi> Who ſhall ſtande before his face when his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation is hote, and in the daye of hys wrath, who ſhall be able to reſiſt? For when he is angrye, the heauens ſhake for feare, the earth quiuereth, the rockes doe breake a ſunder, the mountaines ſhippe, the Lyons rore, the Tygers tremble, and all the inhabitauntes of the worlde are readie to deſire the hilles to couer them. Such is the terrour of his maieſtie, ſuch is the horrour of his diſpleaſure, ſuch is the burning fire of his hote indignation. He will not therefore ſpare thoſe which trayterouſly ſpoyle him of his glorie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue him of his due honor &amp; reuerence, depriue him of his worſhip, who may for
<pb facs="tcp:27972:40"/>
the ſame cauſe, loke for nothing elſe, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, and extreme, horrible, and deadly damnation. For ſéeing he is ielous, and a reuenging Lorde, ſéeing he is a moſt mightie, terrible, and fearefull iudge, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is a God that hath all power, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and rule at his commaundement, ſéeing nothing is able to withſtande hys will, ſéeing neyther place in heauen, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther habitation in earth, nor houſe in Hell is hidden from his preſence: and agayne, ſeing on the otherſide, he is ſo iuſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked, ſo yrefully inflamed, ſo wrathfully mooued, againſt ſuch as robbe him of hys reuerence, it is moſt certaine, and ſo ſure as the Lorde liueth, that they ſhall come to vtter, and extréeme, and moſt miſerable confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond part of the authors diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that is, that they be moſt certaine of the inheritance of heauen which doe exerciſe prayers compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the .vii. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters folowing. <hi>The .xvij. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:27972:40"/>BVt now let vs leaue to ſpeake of thoſe, and conuert our talke to the ſtate of ſuch, as doe with earneſt, humble, and hartie deſire, imbrace the moſt godly exerciſe of prayer. They aſuredlye are moſt certaine to be enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of euerlaſting, and moſt bliſfull ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, for euer and euer eternally. For Chriſt ſaith <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14. <hi>Quicquid petieritis nomine meo, hoc faciam vt glorificetur pater per filium. Si quid petieritis per no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men meum, ego faciam.</hi> Firſt whatſoeuer you ſhall require in my name, that I will bring to paſſe, that the father may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by his ſonne. If you ſhall require any thing in my name I will doe it. Here Chriſt promiſeth vnto vs, that we ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whatſoeuer we ſhall require in his name. If therefore we ſhall require euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life in glorie, and all felicitie with him, and his, Aungels he will gladly, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and readily graunt it vnto vs. For here he is not conſtrayned to promiſe it. Therefore he is willing to graunt it, and againe, he doth not promiſe more, then hée
<pb facs="tcp:27972:41"/>
is able to perfourme, bicauſe he is GOD omnipotent, equall with the father in all power, godhead, and diuinitie. For he ſaith of him ſelfe. My father and I are all one, it remaineth then that of his ſiguler grace, &amp; incredible goodneſſe, wherwith he fauoreth imbraceth, loueth, &amp; tendereth vs, he wil for aſking beſtowe vpon vs ſuch infinite and excéeding commodites, whoſe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; excellency can neither by though of man be conceyued, nor by force of wordes expreſſed. Moreouer he repeateth the ſame in one place, and at one time as it appeareth, the more to confirme vs, to incourage vs, to ſtrengthen vs, to encreaſe our deſire, to pray vnto him, that neyther doubtfulneſſe in aſking, neyther lacke of hope in receyuing, might hinder our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours. In the .15. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> likewiſe he ſaith. <hi>Si manſeritis in me et verba mea in vobis manſerint quicquid volueritis, petetis &amp; fiet vobis.</hi> If you abide in me, and my wordes abide in you, whatſoeuer you will haue, you ſhall aſke, and it ſhall be done, and then he conteyneth theſe wordes in this, my father is glorified, that you bring
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27972:41"/>
forth good fruite plentifully, and be made my diſciples, ſo that by praying vnto him, we ſhal glorify his name, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by that meanes we ſhall be made freſh, and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gardens, fullye repleniſhed with the flouriſhing flowers of moſt excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which will yéelde ſo ſwéete a ſauor to God, and Chriſt our ſauiour, that we ſhall be moſt acceptable ſacrifices, and pleaſant offeringes vnto him. He ſubuerteth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo theſe wordes, which containe incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comfort to the ſolace of ſiely ſoules: Euen as my father hath loued me, ſo I haue loued you: What more ioye and pleaſure? What ſo much comfort can we conceyue? What earneſt loue of Chriſt Ieſus towardes vs maye we gather of this, that he loueth vs, as his father hath loued him? His father to ſhewe his loue towardes him, ſpake on this ſorte out of a clowde: This is my beloued ſonne, in whome I am well pleaſed. Him he rayſed from death to life, from earth to heauen, from cruell croſſe, &amp; affliction, to an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall crowne of glorie immortall, and hath ſet him on his right hande in all power,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:42"/>
and dominion, and hath made his enimies his footeſtoole, all which doe well declare his loue, he beareth towardes him. Nay he loueth him, as he loueth his owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or his owne ſelfe. For he is God of the ſame ſubſtance, that his father is. Let vs therefore be ſure that if we call vppon him with feruent, and humble, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye prayer, hée will heare vs, hee wyll ſanctifie vs, he will direct vs, he will leade vs in all holyneſſe, and pureneſſe of life, and he will preſerue our ſoules, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to euerlaſting felicitie. For ſo he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs, as his father hath loued him. And Chriſt ſayth in an other place. <hi>Beati pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peres ſpiritu, quoniam illorum eſt reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num coelorum.</hi> Bleſſed are the poore in ſpirite, for theirs is the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And to be poore in ſpirite, is nothing elſe, but to humble himſelfe before the face of God, to put awaye all confidence in himſelfe, to craue mercie for his commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wickedneſſe, to poure out his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint before his onely redéemer, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his owne vnworthyneſſe, to confeſſe his weakeneſſe, not to boſt of his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27972:42"/>
merites, not to bragge with boldneſſe, his owne abilitie, not to truſt in his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings, but to lye proſtrate before the iudgement ſeate of God, to wayte for the cru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of mercy, that fall from the Lords table, to cal, and cry for grace, and bounty, through Chriſt Ieſus his death, and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by whome alone he ſeeketh for reliefe, health, and comforte in all humylitie. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, we haue a ſure promiſe of Chriſt himſelfe, ſaying vnto vs. 16 of. <hi>Iohn.</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, verily, I ſay vnto you, whatſoeuer you ſhall require my father in my name, he will giue it you. Aſke, and you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue. If then we ſhall deſire God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the merites of his moſt dearelye beloued ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, to water our harts with the dew of his heauenly grace, and to refreſh our hungry ſoules, with the foode of his holye worde, and ſtill to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, protect, and gouerne our heauie hartes, wyth the wiſedome of his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſpirite, he will no doubt aſſiſt vs, helpe vs, heale vs, direct vs, ſhadow vs with the wings of his mercy, and at the laſt, when our ſoule is diſſolued from the pryſon of
<pb facs="tcp:27972:43"/>
the body, will place it in eternall paradiſe. For Chriſt is the truth, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye, and he hath promiſed faithfully to fulfill all our godly deſires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>The compariſon of God vnto the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Iudge, which is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with continuall, and importune ſute. <hi>The .xviij. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd he the more to encourage vs, doth make a compariſon. <hi>Luke.</hi> 18. betwixt his father, and an vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudge, on this maner. There was a Iudge in a certaine Citie, ſayth he, who neyther feared God, nor eſtéemed man. There was alſo a widow in the ſame citie, and came vnto him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Reuenge me of mine aduerſary, and for a while he woulde not. But at the laſt he ſayde within himſelfe: Although I neyther feare God, nor care for man, yet bycauſe this widowe ſtill troubleth me, I will reuenge hir of hir enimie, leaſt at the laſt the come, and reproue me. And the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27972:43"/>
Lorde ſayde, heare what the vnrighteous iudge ſayth. And ſhall not God reuenge his elect people, that cry vnto him night and day, although he differre it? I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that he ſhal reuenge them quickly. Here Chriſt doth expreſſe, and paynt out in liuely colours, the force of earneſt, and harty prayer. For that Iudge, that was of ſo rough, and rigorous a nature, of ſo fierce, and auſtere conditions, of ſo vngen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and cruell diſpoſition, that he diſpyſed the complaints of the poore, regarded not the requeſts of the miſerable, refuſed to giue eare to the cryes of Orphanes, contemned the lamentations of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed people, cared not for thretnings, ſet religion at naught, conſidered not the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſtrokes of Gods vengeaunce, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loked vpon his duetie, gaue himſelfe to vayne pleaſure, and was in wordes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, in witte wilye; in countenaunce terrible, in ieſture fearefull, in lyfe tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, in manners monſtrous, in conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation ſauage, in dealings dreadfull, in hart ſpitefull, in wyll a wolfe, in though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes outragious, in office cruell, in mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb facs="tcp:27972:44"/>
more than manful, and beyonde mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure ful of al iniquity, by the continual cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon of this woman, by hir pitious complaintes, was reformed, and brought to mercie, was contented to deliuer hir from hir oppreſſing enimie, was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to leaue of his olde ſeueritie, or rather careleſſe cruelty in that caſe, and was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to fulfill hir will, to graunt hir requeſt, and to agree to hir deſire, and then Chriſt tranſferreth it to his father, who is our tender fauourer, to ſhewe how much more he woulde be glad to haue vs poure foorth our prayers vnto him that he might ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our willes, and ſhew mercie vnto thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes, that call vpon him. For he doth of his infinite, and excéeding goodneſſe with fayre, and faythfull promiſes allure vs, with bonntiful rewards endeuor to entiſe vs, with offred, &amp; proffred benifits to binde vs, with mercy to moue vs, with kindneſſe to conſtraine vs, with curteſie to call vs, with pittie to prouoke vs, with giftes to gratifie vs, with ready minde to redreſſe, with reaſon to reforme vs, with good wils to winne vs, with loue to leade vs, with
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27972:44"/>
care to cure vs, with ſolace to ſalute vs, with charitie to chaſten vs, with dutie to driue vs, with compaſſion, as it were, to compell vs to come vnto him. For to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs his affection is earneſt, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, his loue large, and liuely, his care incomparable, his good will gracious, his beneuolence bountiful, his mercy maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. If therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudge, that was ſauage, vniuſt, and terrible, in whome their ſcarce appeared any ſparke of pitie, coulde by a ſimple woman be intreated, howe much more ſhall ſo louing a Lorde, ſo natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affectioned a father, ſo mercifull a God, as this the God of Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob is, be readie to receiue vs?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>That the deuils impreſsion is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered of God to preuayle, where prayer is in place, with the remedies of ſinnes. <hi>The xix. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT the laſt, our ſauiour Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth, that God wil here the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his elect, that crye vnto him, day and night, and will reuenge
<pb facs="tcp:27972:45"/>
them quickly. Where we haue to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that if the Deuill go about, eyther by force to ouerthrow vs, or by pollicye, to plague vs, or by ſleightes to conquere vs, or by ſtrength to ouercome vs, by pleaſure to allure vs, or by paine to compell vs, by trenchynges to vndermine vs, or by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce to leade vs, by foly to force vs, or by fondeneſſe to féede vs, by riches to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs, or by power to conſtraine vs, by villanie to wreſt vs, or by pleaſure to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trappe vs, or by what meanes ſo euer he minde to be victor ouer vs, we may by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for helpe at the mercifull handes of almightie God confounde his deuiſes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertourne his endeuours, and become valiaunt conquerers in all temptations. For if pride doe prick vs, we may call for humilitie with humble obedience, if ſloth, and ydleneſſe, doe créepe into our bodyes, mindes, or members, we may praye for agilitie, loue of labour, and diligence, if the inſatiable thirſt of corruptible treaſure doe couetouſly conſume vs, we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt the gracious vertue of louely liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, frée gentleneſſe, and bountie, if grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27972:45"/>
glottonie doe gréedily deuour vs, we may waite for the aſſured ſtaye of truſtie temperance, if the burning feauer of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and wanton luſt doe miſerably vexe vs, we may deſire the colde, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reliefe of right reaſon, &amp; ruly religion, if the venimous poyſon of bitter enuie do daungerouſlye infect vs, we may require the holeſome medicine of godly charitie, if the loue of licentious libertie doe leade vs, we maye with ſupplication aſke for moderation, and méekeneſſe, if churliſhe, and curriſhe, and careliſhe doggedneſſe hath odiouſly affected vs, we maye wiſhe for gentle, and curteous, and chéerefull hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, to poſſeſſe vs, if contempt of Gods worde hath any time eſtraunged vs from our bounden dueties, we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeche him to beſtowe vpon vs for his mercies ſake the loue of his lawes, and regarde of oure office towardes him, and he aſſuredlye for his promiſe ſake for the merites, and deſerts of Chriſt Ieſus, our Sauiour, for his honour, and glorie, for the maintenaunce of our eſtate, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of our comfort, for the helth of our
<pb facs="tcp:27972:46"/>
ſoules, which he greatlye tendereth, wyll giue vs all theſe vertues with floudes of his grace, &amp; ſtreames of his mercie, to the drowning of ſinne &amp; to the confirmation, eſtabliſhing, &amp; erection of al goodneſſe, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and true fayth, &amp; perfite charitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>The applying of the Prodigall ſonne vnto the repentaunt ſinner by prayer. <hi>The .xx. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr he requireth or deſireth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than our conuerſion vnto him, our helth, and ſafetie, our ioye, ſolace, and commoditie, our life and libertie, as it appeareth by the loſt ſonne in the. 15. of <hi>Luke,</hi> who after he receyued his portion of ſubſtance, went into a ſtraunge countrie, &amp; there riotouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpent all, inſomuch, that at the laſt, hée by the force of pinching pouertie, hard fortune, and néedefull neceſſitie, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to féede hogges, and deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> bée nouryſhed wyth ſuch prouendour, as the ſwine were filled, and fatted withall,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27972:46"/>
but no man gaue any vnto him, at length when he was almoſt ſterued for lacke of neceſſarie ſuſtinaunce, and in ſuch pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous plight, and miſerable eſtate, that lyfe was almoſt readye to forſake his carefull carkaſſe, he thought this within himſelfe. Manye hyred ſeruauntes in my fathers houſe haue plentie of vittayles, and I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe for hunger. I will riſe and go to my father, and will ſaye vnto him: Father I haue ſinned againſt heauen, and before thée, nowe I am not worthye to be called thy ſonne, make me as one of thy hyred ſeruaunts. And he roſe, and came to his father. But when he was yet a farre off, his father ſaw him, and being moued with mercie came running towardes him, and fell vpon his neck, &amp; kiſſed him. Sée how his loue is not chaunged, his good affection is not mooued, his tender fauour is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, yea rather his ioy in him is now encreaſed, his gracious goodneſſe maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly enlarged, his pittie more plentifully prouoked towards his loſt ſonne, although before he had wilfully diſobeyed his father, contemptiouſly refuſed to tarie with him,
<pb facs="tcp:27972:47"/>
diſobediently wandred into forraine coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, riotouſly royſted, and raunged in ſtraunge lands, wantonly waſted his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per portion of ſubſtaunce, letherouſly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed his ſtore vpon ſtrumpets, prodigal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye poured out his iuſt inheritaunce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vagabonds, yea, although he was nowe in ſuche a caſe, that his eſtate was ſuccourleſſe, his purſe penyleſſe, his hart hopeleſſe, his ſkinne diſcoloured, his fleſh withered, his beautie deformed, his come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe defaced, his body weried, his welth waſted, his ſtrength weakened, his force vaniſhed, his life ſorowfull, his minde mournefull, his deſperate degrée miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſcornefull, his plight pitifull, and his perſon ſlaunderouſlye ſpoken off, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious, ſée for all this howe louingly he entertayneth him, howe graciouſly he receyueth him, how gently he kiſſeth him, howe readily he runneth to méete him, to ſalute him, to welcome him home againe, and then the ſonne ſeing his father ſo to fauour him, repenteth him of his former diſobedience, bewayleth his vngracious dealing, and is hartily ſorie for his former
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27972:47"/>
behauour, and ſpeaketh on ſuch maner, as he had before determined: Father I haue ſinned againſt heauen, and againſt thée, and am vnworthie hereafter to hée called thy ſonne. But his father ſaid to his ſeruants. Bring forth the beſt garment, &amp; put it on him, and put a ring on hys hand, and ſhoes on his féete, and bring hither the fatte calfe, and kil him, and let vs eate, and be merie. For this my ſonne was deade, and is aliue againe, he was loſt, and is nowe founde, and they began to be merie. This Father, that the Parable ſpeaketh off, is God our Creator, our heauenly father, our mightie maker, that placed man in Paradyſe, who like a lewde, and diſſolute ſonne went a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring from the ſwéete fieldes of vertues, into the vnknowne woodes, and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous mariſhes of wicked diſobedience, and returning vnto his Father, driuen therevnto by neceſſitie, was ioyfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, opening, and humbly confeſſing, and therewithall lamenting his former wickedneſſe, only cleaueth vnto the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, and deſertes of our Sauiour
<pb facs="tcp:27972:48"/>
Chriſt Ieſus. Thus therefore he loueth vs ſo feruently, that he remembreth no our former wickedneſſe, when once wée ſhall call vppon him, but will with ioye graunt, and giue vnto vs a wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is, conſtant faith, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, iuſtification thorowe Chriſt Ieſus, that with the ſame we being apparelled, may be preſent at the kings feaſt wythout ſhame, or confuſion. Thus by prayers poured out vnto God, we ſhall with the fiue wiſe Virgines haue Oyle ſufficient in our Lampes to maintaine the light, and ſhall enter into the Palace of the bridegrome with ioy, and gladneſſe, and all felicitie. Thus we ſhall enter into the kingdome, which God hath prepared for himſelfe, and his Aungels, there to inioye the crowne of immortall glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>The example of the theefe hanging on the right hande of Chriſt, applied to the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of prayer. <hi>The .xxi. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:27972:48"/>HEre I might with examples, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the force, and effect of prayer, but for breuitie ſake, I will onely ſet before your eyes the example of the théefe, which was hanged vpon the right hand of Chriſt at his paſſion. He, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had paſſed his life in ſuch ſort, that there appeared no way, but eternall damnation, vnleſſe by méere mercy he had béene receyued, called vppon Chriſt for grace, and mercy, deſiring him with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, penitent, and oppreſſed hart, with har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie contrition, with earneſt repentaunce, with conſtaunt, liuely, and ſtedfaſt fayth, to remember him when he came to hys kingdome, to deliuer him from the power of the deuill, who was readie to receyue him, to purge him from his vncleanneſſe, wherwith he before had defaced the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of God, that was placed in his owne breſt, &amp; had, as it were, deſperatly throwne himſelfe in the moſt cruell, and horrible bondage of curſſed Sathan. But by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for the louing mercies, and incredible goodneſſe of Chriſt Ieſus, then hanging vpon the croſſe for the redemption of him
<pb facs="tcp:27972:49"/>
and all mankinde, miſerably plunged in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o a Sea of miſeries, was by the raunſome of his moſt precious bloud moſt happily deliuered. For after he had poured out his humble, and hartie prayers, his pityous complaints, his wofull wretchedneſſe, his ſorowfull ſighes, his repentaunt teares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he heard this comfortable anſwere. This daye thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe. Loe the readineſſe of Chriſt Ieſus in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing our prayers, in graunting ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peticions, in wyping awaye our wofull wéeping, in rewarding them, that turne vnto him, in comforting them, that ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully doe ſéeke him, and in exalting, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and glorifying them, that faythfully doe folowe him in workes, in wyll, in truth, in truſt, in obedience, and earneſt charitie. This théefe was, as it may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in his yong, &amp; tender age, lewdely, loſely, and diſſolutely brought vp, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nurtered, vnaduiſedly inſtructed, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarded, trayned vp in euill company, foſtered in all abhomination, rapine, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, ſtealing, ſpoyling, and ſuch like, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reſpecting the ſeuere iuſtice, or gentle
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27972:49"/>
dealing, the rigorous ſeueritie, or louing mercies of God almightie, the iudge of all men, vntill his laſt ende approched, and then being terrified with remorſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and driuen into extreme agony with the remembrance of his wicked life, knowing that he coulde not eſcape moſt terrible vengeaunce, vnleſſe he ſhould flie to the preſent comfort of Gods méere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, then relented, and charitably rebuked his fellowe théefe for deſpyſing, and reuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Chriſt Ieſus, and then faithfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vppon Chriſt, was paciently, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye, and readilye receyued, and as Chriſte promyſed, was that ſame daye brought vp into the moſt pleaſant region of heauenlye delites euer to enioye an immortall crowne of eternall felicitie. O moſt blyſful eſtate obtayned by prayer. O the maruellous mercies of Chriſt our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. O the moſt happie hope of a repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunt hart. He is crowned with immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall glorie, which hath worthily deſerued extréeme miſerie. He is accoumpted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of eternall ſaluation, which for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertes ſhoulde rather be condemned wyth
<pb facs="tcp:27972:50"/>
deadly damnation. He is deliuered from the power, bondage, and crueltie of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, which all his lyfe time for the moſt part hath vowed, and yelded his ſeruice to all impietie, going to warfare vnder the banner of the deuill, a tormenting tyrant. This miraculous effect, and incomparable worke was brought to paſſe by pouring out of his penſiue heart, moſt wofull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, with hope in Gods mercies tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the manifolde merits of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, our onely redéemer, to be deliuered from preſent daunger of his damnable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts. If therefore we thinke that Chriſt is able to perfourme that, which he hath promiſed, if we think that his arme is not abridged, if we thinke him not to be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, if we beléeue his faithfull promiſes, if we giue credite to his reuealed worde, and holy goſpel, if we doubt not of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercies, if we think that his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud, poured out moſt plentifully vpon the aultar of the croſſe, haue ſtill his force for our iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we muſt alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily knowe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with the poore widowe, we ſhal obtain our requeſt, thorow earneſt
<pb facs="tcp:27972:50"/>
prayer at God his hande, that through him we ſhall be able to daunt the power of the Deuill, that with the loſt ſonne we ſhall of our father be ioyfullye receyued, that with the repentant théefe we ſhall reigne in Paradiſe for euer and euer in all felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For hartie prayer cannot be without ſtedfaſt faith. 1. Iacob. <hi>Poſtulet in fide, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil heſitans,</hi> let him pray in fayth nothing doubting at all. And Paule ſayth. <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo inuocabunt eum, in quem non crediderunt,</hi> howe ſhall they call vppon him, in whome they haue not beléeued? Fayth bringeth a ſuretie of eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. For. 3. Iohn, ſo God loued the worlde, that he gaue his onely begotten ſonne for this purpoſe, that euerye one, which beléeueth on him, ſhoulde not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, but haue lyfe euerlaſting. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, in the ende of the ſame Chapter, it is written. He that beléeueth the wordes, which the ſonne of God ſpeaketh, hath life euerlaſting. And in the fift Chapter, it is ſayde. Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, hée that heareth my wordes, and beleueth in him, that ſent me, hath eternall lyfe. And
<pb facs="tcp:27972:51"/>
in the ſixt Chapter we reade. <hi>Haec eſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas patris mei. &amp;c.</hi> This is the will of my father, which ſent me, that euery one, that ſéeth the ſonne, and beléeueth on him, ſhould haue eternall lyfe. Alſo in the ſame place: Verily I ſay vnto you, he that belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me, hath euerlaſting lyfe. And Iohn alſo in the .xx. chapter hath theſe wordes: <hi>Haec aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcripta ſunt. &amp;c.</hi> Theſe things are written, that you may beleue that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is Chriſt, the ſonne of God, and that beleuing, you may haue lyfe thorowe his name. And another ſayth, <hi>laetabuntur om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, qui ſperant in te, in aeternum exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabunt,</hi> all ſhall reioyce, that truſt in thée (O Lord) they ſhall for euer be moſt glad, and ioyfull. It is therfore euident, that all thoſe, which with conſtant hope, and ſure fayth, and contrite hart, &amp; humble minde, call vpon God in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall be deliuered from the deceites of the Deuill, and ſhall enioye for euer an incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible crowne of immortall glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:27972:51"/>
               <head>The concluſion of the ſeconde part of the Authors diuiſion, with nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble teſtimonies thereof out of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>The .xxij. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt what hath ſo bewitched oure mindes, or benummed our ſenſes, or bereaued vs of our right vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that we ſo ſluggiſhely, nay vnreaſonably doe neglect our dueties to God, not regarding our owne commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, welth, happie eſtate, and felicitie, but rather voluntarilie running into wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doe deſerue moſt déepe daungers, and deadly miſeries, and dolefull damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Chriſt commaundeth vs carefullye, faythfully, continually to call vpon him with hartie prayers, and we refuſe to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe him. That open enimie of mankind, Sathan, chargeth vs to liue in ſléepie, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſlothfull ſecuritie, and we readily conforme our ſelues to his curſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. Chriſt came downe from
<pb facs="tcp:27972:52"/>
his celeſtiall throne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> glorious, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall maieſtie to ſéeke vs which were loſt, and wandring, and wayward ſhéepe, driuen from the folde, by the craftie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyaunce of the ſubtile Serpent, and we vngratefully refuſe the exceeding gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and meere mercy of him, that ſéeketh our ſaluation. Sathan, when we were in the fauour of God, ſubtilly deceyued vs, and miſerably plunged vs into the terrible ſeas of Gods heauie vengeaunce, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, yet hym we fréely doe folow in all our attemptes and endeuours. Chriſt promyſeth vs eternall life in heauenly ioy, ſolace, and all felicitie, if we will kéepe his commaundements, and call vpon him, yet we wilfully deſpiſe him. Sathan wil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, that we ſhall liue, or rather die in terrible flames of hell fire, in all dolour, griefe, and miſerable anguiſh, if we frame our liues according to his deuiliſhe deſire, and yet we delite to liue in his obedience. O ſtraunge maner of outragious mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Shall bitter ſorrowes, for euer to endure, be preferred before incomparable ioyes, which neuer haue ende? Shall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:27972:52"/>
be ſatiſfied, and our euer lyuing, and almightie God be wrathfully diſpleaſed? Shall we loue a deuouring enimy, &amp; leaue our louing Lord? God forbid. Let vs nowe proſtrate our ſelues before the iudgement ſeat of God, let vs lament our miſerie, let vs crie for grace, and mercy, with continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prayer, that we may for all our ſinnes obtaine remiſſion, that we may not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed in the day of the Lorde, when the hidden thoughtes of our ſecrete mindes, ſhall openly be declared, and for the ſame, moſt iuſt iudgement ſeuerely pronounced. Let vs no more lye groueling vppon the grounde wyth the hatefull ſerpent, but let vs ſet our thoughtes, and hartes a lofte wyth the chaſt turtle doue, that is, let vs forſake earthly, fond, and deuiliſh delites, let vs not ſet our harts vpon worldly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, let vs not féede vpon vaine pleaſures, and fading fantaſies, but let vs lodge with Chriſt Ieſus in heauen, or rather let vs haue him lodging in our breſtes, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing our harts, &amp; directing our thoughts which we ſhall eaſily obtayne, if wyth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt hartes we offer vnto him the
<pb facs="tcp:27972:53"/>
ſacrifice of prayer, and thankeſgiuing. For ſeing that he did vouchſafe to come downe from heauen, to clenſe vs, when we were deformed, and depraued with the foule ſpottes, and blemiſhes of deadly ſinne, he will now much more, if we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and hartily requeſt the ſame, make vs méete veſſels to receyue the moſt hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and comfortable bleſſing of the holy ghoſt, that we may continue, in his moſt gracious fauour. But this is ſufficient for the godly minded members of Chriſt, and to them eſpeciallye doth belong the ſure hope of eternall happineſſe. Thoſe I call the members of Chriſt, which haue alwayes a cleare conſcience before the face of God, and men, and alſo thoſe (for of the former ſorte there are very fewe) which although they haue béene polluted with the filthineſſe of wicked, and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable impietie, yet now at the laſt, are returned from the ſame vngodlineſſe, and with all diligence, loue, and obedience, doe imbrace the Goſpell, abhorre hypocriſie, deteſt their former vilanie, and ſequeſter themſelues from blinde ſecuritie. Such
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27972:53"/>
I ſay, ſhall be ſure by prayer, to obtayne eternall ſaluation. For before God they are counted iuſt through the merites of Chriſt Ieſus, and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth, that the prayer of the iuſt man preuayleth much.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>The thirde parte of the Authors diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that is, the waye how to be hearde in our prayer, with a definition of it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſing two Chapters. <hi>The .xxiij. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw I will (by the fauour of god) ſpeake a worde or two of the laſt poynt, that is, how we maye ſo pray, that we may be hearde, and obtayne our requeſt. Here I thinke, that it be moſt neceſſarie for me to vſe in this matter, ſuch breuitie, as is moſt méete for thoſe, to whome I direct this my talke. I ſpeake onely of thoſe, which be rude, and ignoraunt in this caſe, and that haue bene through méere ſimplicitie blinded by the vaile of curſed poperie, and not to ſuch, as
<pb facs="tcp:27972:54"/>
obſtinately harden their harts and ſhutte their eyes, and ſtop their eares, that they may not be healed. To ſuch as theſe, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ignoraunt, and ſéely ſoules be, bréefe notes, without large diſcourſe, is vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly moſt commodious. I will therfore in a ſhorte difinition, firſt ſhew what pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is, and then will adioyne thoſe proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as it were, which are neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to faythfull, and true prayer. For by this meanes they may the ſooneſt learn the maner of true prayer, and beare it in memorie. Subtilly to diſpute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyuers kinds of prayer, &amp; ſuch like, rather belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to curious ſchoolemen in vniuerſities, than to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimple chriſtians in their priuate houſes, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon churches. Prayer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a religious declaration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde before God, wherin we deſire w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> earneſt affection, either to be preſerued from dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity ſpiritual, or temporall, either to enioy ſome deſired benifit belong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to ſoule, or body, either elſe wherin we yelde moſt hartie thankes for ſome recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued benifite. Bycauſe here be mentioned diuers kindes of benifites to be deſired, as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27972:54"/>
neceſſitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gods handes, wée muſt know tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are not without dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference all to be requeſted after one ſort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For thoſe things, which belong to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, are alwayes to be requeſted with a condition, that is, if they be not hurtfull for the ſoule, if it be Gods good pleaſure to graunt them, if it be for the glorie of God to condiſcende to our requeſt. But ſuch things, as tende to the ſafegarde of the ſoule to heauenly felicitie, to godly chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with ſuch lyke, are to be deſired ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply without condition of bodily welth, or worldly ſafety. Theſe things well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we muſt obſerue theſe rules folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if we will obtayne our requeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſixe rules, which muſt bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to obtaine our requeſts wythall. <hi>The .xxiiij. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FFirſt we muſt direct our prayers to God alone, our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not to Aungels, deade ſainctes, Deuils, ſtocks, ſtones, or ſuch lyke. For it is written, thou
<pb facs="tcp:27972:55"/>
ſhalt worſhippe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, and him onely ſhalt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſerne.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. <hi>Math.</hi> 4.</note> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, God ſaith in Eſay, the .43. <hi>Ego ſum, ego ſum. &amp;c.</hi> I am, I am, and without me there is no ſauiour. And .45. Chapter. A iuſt and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, there is none but I. And ſuch places there are to be founde a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which for breuitie ſake I of purpoſe doe omitte, partly bicauſe of the rude, and ſimple peoples ſake, that they may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter remember theſe rules, and partly by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a notable treatiſe, againſt the worſhipping, &amp; inuocation of ſaintes, now extaunt, wherin this queſtion is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye debated, by <hi>Iohn Veron,</hi> a worthye member of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly, we muſt poure out oure ſupplications before God, in all humilitie, truſting fauourably to be accepted onely for the merites, &amp; paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, who is our onely ſatiſfaction, iuſtification, and righteouſneſſe before the Lorde, &amp; not for the worthineſſe of our owne workes. For Chriſt Ieſus, when we were accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed came downe from heauen to delyuer vs from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſe whervnto al we were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27972:55"/>
&amp; was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>crifice for our ſinnes. Wherevpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h,<note place="margin">Ephe.</note> ye are ſaued by grace through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, and that not of our ſelues, for it is the gift of God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not of workes, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdely, they which preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before God to requeſt any thing of him, muſt caſt of all cruelty, violence, and oppreſſion towardes other. For in <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1. we read: When you ſhall ſtretch out your handes, I will turne mine eies from you, and when you ſhal multiply your praiers, I will not heare you, ſayth the Lorde. For your hands be full of bloud. Waſhe your ſelues, and be cleane. They muſt put all vnmercifulneſſe out of their mindes. For in the .xxj. of the Prouerbes, it is written: He that ſtoppeth his eare at the cry of the poore, ſhall cry himſelfe, and not be heard. This is plaine by the example of Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, and the riche Glutton. They muſt plucke out of their hartes all enuye, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, malice, and diſſenſion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.</note> they muſt forgiue the faultes of their brethren. For Chriſt ſayth: When ye ſtande to praye
<pb facs="tcp:27972:56"/>
forgiue your brothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſixt of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew. If you for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> euen from the bottome of your hart, neyther ſhall your father which is in heauen forgiue you. They muſt be humble, and baniſhe away all pride, or diſdaine, oute of the cloſet of their minde. For Pſalme. 51: An humble and contrite heart, God will not deſpiſe. And Peter ſaith: God reſiſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prowde, &amp; giueth grace to the humble.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 5.</note> Examples hereof be the prowde Phariſey, and poore Publicane, in the goſpell. They muſt be ſure, ſtedfaſt, and conſtaunt in fayth. For it is ſaid: Let him aſke in fayth, doubting nothing. <hi>Iacob.</hi> 10. They muſt with harty, ſincere, and true repentaunce, bewayle their ſinfull wickedneſſe, and wicked wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and haue an earneſt deſire to ſet forth the glorie of God, to liue in due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God, and his goſpell, to ſubuert the raging affections of the corrupt fleſhe vnto the heauenly, pure, and angelicall motions of the ſpirite, they muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with a feruencie of ſpirite, ioyned to continuance in ſupplication, and not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27972:56"/>
come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art, and a babling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or chalenge the hart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ard apperance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe both haſt and mouth agrée ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ly in one kinde of worſhip, it cannot he pleaſant vnto God nor Chriſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> is ſayd of ſome, this people honoreth me with their lips, but their hart is farre from me. Such God will ſpue out of hys mouth, and vtterly refuſe them. Briefly theſe rules maye be thus concluded. They, which minde to obtayne their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes, when they yéelde vp their ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, muſt direct the ſame to God, in the name of Chriſt Ieſus, but ſo that they themſelues be in minde mercyfull, in manners milde, in loue charitable, in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection amyable, in fayth conſtant, in lyfe obedient, in ſpirite feruent, and in hart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt. Nowe moreouer, there be other circumſtances, which are to be annexed, as when, where, for whom, for what things, with what ieſture, after what manner we ought to pray.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:27972:57"/>
               <head>The circumſtances, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h ought to be obſerued in prayer, beſide the ſixe rules. <hi>The .xxv. Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the firſt it is written, <hi>indeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenter orat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> pray continually, that is, whenſoeuer you ſhall be aſſaulted with temptation, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in proſperitie, or in aduerſitie, call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, not that at all times without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or intermiſſion we ſhould onely be occupied in prayer, but that we ſhould as godly men haue done before time, appoint certayne tymes to poure out our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaintes before God, &amp; alſo at other times in what thing ſoeuer we be occupied, in ſpirite, in truth, in ſighes, in thought, in worke, in will, call vpon God for the helpe of his grace, and acceſſe of his mercie. As the Ploughman at his labour, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt at his occupying, the Scholer at his ſtudie, and ſo forth, ought not onely at certaine houres giue himſelfe to prayer, but alſo when he is moſt occupied, ought
<pb facs="tcp:27972:57"/>
in he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with God through prayer in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>es, but eſpecially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, in the congregation of chriſtians. For when many togither in one ſpirit yéelde vp their prayers, then are they moſte accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, and gracious to Chriſt, our Sauiour.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For the thirde, we ought to praye for the good, and proſperous eſtate of godlye Princes, and magiſtrates, and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, it belongeth to our bounden duties, to beſeech God in the bowels of mercye to preſerue for the glorye of his holy name our good, and gracious ſoueraigne, Ladie Quéene Elizabeth, in theſe troubleſome times from all daunger in moſt happie eſtate, and felicitie, which I beſéech him to doe for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, in whome he is well pleaſed, to the ſubuerſion of hir enimies, the mayntenaunce of true rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and confuſion of curſed Sathan. Then we ought to pray, for the good eſtate of Gods holy Miniſters, for our ſelues, for
<pb facs="tcp:27972:58"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> fleſh, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e they be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> out of the priſon of the body. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they raigne with Chriſt, or dye wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Deuilles, where there is no redemption.</p>
               <p n="4">4 For the fourth, we may praye for things pertayning to the neceſſitie of the body, and of the ſoule, and for eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in Ieſus Chriſt, alwayes in all prayers hauing reſpect to our own ſelues, and to the will of God, that we aſke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which eyther is not competent for our eſtate, or not agreable to the glory of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5 For the fifte, we may vſe any comely ieſture, eyther knéeling, or ſtanding, or ſitting, as preſent occaſion ſhall moue vs, ſo that we haue an humble minde, and contrite hart, in all our prayers.</p>
               <p n="6">6 For the ſixt, we may vſe the forme of prayer, that Chriſt hath taught vs, or any other, not repugnaunt to the ſame, or vſe ſuch wordes as the preſent eſtate wyll gyue occaſion vnto, as Chriſt did in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27972:58"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, not alwayes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reciſely that prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only called the lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or things, as certayne circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>es conſidered, let vs now ſearch out the effect of prayer, which may eaſily be perceyued by examples taken out of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Ioſuae.</hi> 10. By prayer the Sunne ſtoode in the middle of heauen, the ſpace of a whole day. <hi>Moyſes</hi> by prayer wrought meruellous effectes. Samſon, Samuel, Elias, Dauid, Ezechias, Salamon, Anna, Cornelius, Paule, and Silas, wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye preuayled by force of prayer, as in ſcriptures manifeſtly is declared. But of theſe things no man meanely conuerſant in ſcriptures can be ignoraunt. Therfore without longer diſcourſe, I will make an ende. And here I beſéeche thée (good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (to call to minde the threates of God againſt obſtinate ſinners, the plagues of God executed againſt rebellious perſons, the daungerous, and miſerable eſtate of harde harted chriſtians, and ſo perhaps thou ſhalt be touched with feare of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhe, and extreme miſery. Then ponder
<pb facs="tcp:27972:59"/>
in thy minde wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hartie prayer, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath prouided for them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſuire to him in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> eternall felicitie thou ſhalt enioy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> earneſt ſupplication, thou craue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nde his grace, &amp; mercy. And laſt of all, in conſideration of theſe things, let prayer be thy continuall exerciſe, and dayly prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. For prayer is the quietneſſe of them, which be tormoyled, the reſt of them, that are moleſted, the hauen of them, which ſuffer ſhipwracke, the comfort of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, the ſalue of the ſinfull, the ſhielde of the fearefull, the hope of the helpeleſſe, the holde of the harbourleſſe, the helpe of the hopeleſſe, the ſolace of the comfortleſſe. Prayer is in welth a ſafegarde, in health a preſeruatiue, in griefe a gracious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, in warre a ſword, in peace a garden of delites, in bondage libertie, in ſorow ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in death lyfe, in penurie a ſtorehouſe of all things neceſſarie. And to conclude, prayer is the readie path, to the pleaſaunt paſture, of eternall Paradiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:27972:59"/>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> great,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pe,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>las</hi> princely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de what foyzen fertyle ſprings,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from the learned ſkill:</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f thoſe that trauell earneſtly,</l>
            <l>to clyme <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> hill.</l>
            <l>Beholde what youthfull yeres can doe,</l>
            <l>through great ſtudie, and paine:</l>
            <l>Beholde what knowledge tender age,</l>
            <l>by labour can attaine.</l>
            <l>This little booke ſo well compact,</l>
            <l>deſerueth worthy prayſe:</l>
            <l>Which the Authour hath publiſhed,</l>
            <l>a mirror in theſe dayes.</l>
            <l>A mirror? yea, a looking glaſſe,</l>
            <l>for ſo I may him name:</l>
            <l>Bycauſe by ſacred ſcripture he</l>
            <l>his firſt attempt doth frame.</l>
            <l>The ſtile of ſome is prayſed much,</l>
            <l>that fayned ſtories write:</l>
            <l>Collected out of Poets workes,</l>
            <l>for that they doe delite,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:27972:60"/>And pleaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Then wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for due rewarde</l>
            <l>deſerue, that vertuouſly</l>
            <l>Doth vſe his tallent, which he hath</l>
            <l>obtayned painefully?</l>
            <l>Eternall prayſe, as I doe iudge,</l>
            <l>and fame that aye ſhall dure:</l>
            <l>For vayne delites doe vaniſhe all,</l>
            <l>when vertue ſhineth pure.</l>
            <l>The worde of God, mans ſoule doth féede,</l>
            <l>the ſcripture bringeth light:</l>
            <l>But fonde, and fooliſh tales are naught.</l>
            <l>Therfore as willeth right,</l>
            <l>The Authors enterpriſe commende,</l>
            <l>conceiue his good intent:</l>
            <l>Commende his trauell, which he hath</l>
            <l>in ſacred ſcripture ſpent.</l>
            <l>Then truly ſhall you ſtirre him vp,</l>
            <l>as now he hath begonne:</l>
            <l>So to procéede, and faythfully,</l>
            <l>this kinde of race to runne.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27972:60"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
